<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vindication, or, The parallel of the French Holy-League and the English League and Covenant turn'd into a seditious libell against the King and His Royal Highness by Thomas Hunt and the authors of the Reflections upon the pretended parallel in the play called The Duke of Guise / written by Mr. Dryden.</title>
            <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12340594</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12340594</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 208:10e)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vindication, or, The parallel of the French Holy-League and the English League and Covenant turn'd into a seditious libell against the King and His Royal Highness by Thomas Hunt and the authors of the Reflections upon the pretended parallel in the play called The Duke of Guise / written by Mr. Dryden.</title>
                  <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jacob Tonson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An answer to Thomas Hunt's Defence of the charter, 1683, and to Thomas Shadwell's Some reflections, 1683.</note>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Worcester College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hunt, Thomas, 1627?-1688. --  Defence of the charter, and municipal rights of the city of London.</term>
               <term>Shadwell, Thomas, 1642?-1692. --  Some reflections upon the pretended parallel in the play called The Duke of Guise.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199796:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199796:1"/>
            <p>THE VINDICATION: OR THE PARALLEL OF THE <hi>FRENCH</hi> HOLY-LEAGUE, AND THE. Engliſh League and Covenant, Turn'd into a Seditious Libell againſt the KING and his ROYAL HIGHNESS, BY <hi>Thomas Hunt</hi> and the Authors of the <hi>Reflections</hi> upon the Pretended Parallel in the Play called The DUKE of <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ISE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by Mr. <hi>DRYDEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Turno tempus erit magno cùm optaverit emptum</l>
               <l>Intactum Pallanta: &amp; cùm ſpolia iſta, diem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Oderit.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jacob Tonſon</hi> at the <hi>Judges Head</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane,</hi> near <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 
               <abbr>MDCLXXXIII.</abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:199796:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199796:2"/>
            <head>THE VINDICATION OF THE Duke of Guiſe.</head>
            <p>IN the Year of His Majeſty's Happy Reſtauration, the Firſt Play I undertook was <hi>the Duke of Guiſe,</hi> as the Faireſt way, which <hi>the Act of Indempnity</hi> had then left us, of ſetting forth the <hi>Riſe</hi> of the <hi>Late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion;</hi> and by <hi>Exploding</hi> the Villanies of it upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> to <hi>Precaution Poſterity</hi> againſt the Like Errors.</p>
            <p>As This was my <hi>Firſt Eſſay;</hi> ſo it met with the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfiniſht Piece;</hi> that is to ſay, It was Damn'd in Private, by the Advice of ſome Friends to whom I ſhew'd it; who freely told me, that it was an Excellent Subject; but not ſo Artificially wrought, as they could have wiſh'd: And now let my Enemies make their Beſt of This Confeſſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scene</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>'s <hi>Return</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> AGAINST the King's <hi>Poſitive Command,</hi> was then written; I have the Copy of it ſtill by me, almoſt the ſame which it now remains, being taken <hi>Verbatim</hi> out of <hi>Davila:</hi> For where the <hi>Action</hi> is <hi>Remarkable,</hi> and the very <hi>words Related,</hi> the Poet is not at liberty to change them much; and if he will be adding any thing for <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199796:3"/>it ought to be <hi>wholly of a piece.</hi> This do I take for a ſufficient Juſtification of that Scene, unleſs they will make the <hi>pretended Parallel</hi> to be a <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as well as a <hi>Parallel</hi> of <hi>Accidents,</hi> that were <hi>twenty years after to come.</hi> Neither do I find that they can ſuggeſt the leaſt colour for't in any other part of the Tragedy.</p>
            <p>But now comes the main Objection, <hi>Why was it ſtopt then?</hi> To which I ſhall render this juſt Account, with all due Reſpects to thoſe who were the Occaſion of it.</p>
            <p>Upon a wandering Rumour (which I will divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Miſtake</hi>) that ſome Great Perſons were repreſented or perſonated in it, the Matter was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of to my Lord <hi>Chamberlain;</hi> who, thereupon, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Play to be brought to him, and prohibited the Acting of it till further Order; commanding me, after this, to wait upon his Lordſhip; which I did, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſir'd him to compare the <hi>Play</hi> with the <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> from whence the Subject was taken, referring to the <hi>Firſt Scene</hi> of the <hi>Fourth Act,</hi> whereupon the <hi>Exception</hi> was <hi>grounded,</hi> and leaving <hi>Davila</hi> (the <hi>Original</hi>) with his Lordſhip. This was before <hi>Midſummer;</hi> and about two Months after, I receiv'd the Play back again from his Lordſhip, but without any poſitive Order whether it <hi>ſhould</hi> be Acted or <hi>not;</hi> neither was Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> or <hi>my ſelf</hi> any way ſolicitous about it: But this indeed I ever ſaid, That it was intended for the <hi>King's Service;</hi> and <hi>his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> was the beſt <hi>Judge,</hi> whether it anſwer'd that End or no; and that I reckon'd it my duty to ſubmit, if his Majeſty, for any Reaſon whatſoever, ſhould deem it unfit for the <hi>Stage.</hi> In the <hi>interim,</hi> a ſtrict Scrutiny was made, and <hi>no Parallel</hi> of the Great Perſon deſign'd, could be made out. But this Puſh failing, there were immediately ſtarted ſome terrible Inſinuations, that the <hi>Perſon</hi> of his <hi>Majesty</hi> was <hi>repreſented</hi> under that of <hi>Henry the Third;</hi> which if they could have found out, would have conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, perchance, not only in the <hi>ſtopping</hi> of the <hi>Play,</hi> but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199796:3"/>in the <hi>hanging up</hi> of the <hi>Poets.</hi> But ſo it was, that his Majeſty's <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> acquitted both the <hi>One,</hi> and the <hi>Other;</hi> and when the <hi>Play it ſelf</hi> was almoſt <hi>forgotten,</hi> there were Orders given for the <hi>Acting</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>This is Matter of <hi>Fact;</hi> and I have the Honour of ſo Great Witneſſes to the truth of what I have deliver'd, that it will need no other Appeal. As to the Expoſing of any Perſon living, our innocency is ſo clear, that it is almoſt unneceſſary to ſay, <hi>It was not in my Thought;</hi> and as far as any one Man can vouch for another, I do believe it was as little in Mr. <hi>Lee</hi>'s. And now ſince ſome People have been ſo buſie as to caſt out falſe and ſcandalous Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, how far we two agreed upon the Writing of it, I muſt do a common Right both to Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> and <hi>my ſelf,</hi> to declare publickly that it was at his earneſt Deſire, without any Solicitation of mine, that this Play was produced betwixt us. After the writing of <hi>Oedipus,</hi> I paſs'd a Promiſe to joyn with him in another; and he happen'd to claim the performance of that Promiſe, juſt upon the finiſhing of a Poem, when I would have been glad of a little reſpite before the undertaking of a ſecond Task. The Perſon that paſs'd betwixt us, knows this to be true; and Mr. <hi>Lee</hi> himſelf, I am ſure, will not diſown it: So that I did not <hi>[ſeduce him to joyn with me]</hi> as the malicious Authors of the <hi>Reflections</hi> are pleas'd to call it; but Mr. <hi>Lee</hi>'s <hi>Loyalty</hi> is above ſo <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous</hi> a <hi>Slander.</hi> I know very well, that the Town did ignorantly call and take this to be <hi>my Play;</hi> but I ſhall not arrogate to my ſelf the Merits of my Friend. <hi>Two thirds</hi> of it belong'd to <hi>him;</hi> and then to <hi>me</hi> only the <hi>Firſt Scene</hi> of the Play; the whole <hi>Fourth Act,</hi> and the <hi>firſt half,</hi> or ſomewhat <hi>more</hi> of the <hi>Fifth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pamphleteers, I know, do very boldly inſinuate, that <hi>before the Acting of it, I took the whole Play to my ſelf, but finding afterwards how ill ſucceſs it had upon the Stage, I threw as much of it as poſſibly I could upon my Fellow.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199796:4"/>Now here are <hi>three damn'd Lyes</hi> crowded together into a very little room: Firſt, That I <hi>aſſum'd</hi> any part of it to my <hi>ſelf,</hi> which I had not <hi>written;</hi> wherein I appeal, not only to my particular <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> but to the whole Company of <hi>Actors,</hi> who will witneſs for me, that in all the <hi>Rehearſals,</hi> I never pretended to any <hi>one Scene</hi> of Mr. <hi>Lee</hi>'s, but did him all imaginable Right, in his title to the <hi>greater part</hi> of it. I hope, I may, without <hi>Vanity,</hi> affirm to the World, that I never ſtood in need of borrowing another mans Reputation; and I have been as little guilty of the <hi>Injustice,</hi> of laying claim to any thing which was not my own. Nay, I durſt almoſt refer my ſelf to ſome of the angry Poets on the other ſide, whether I have not rather <hi>countenanc'd</hi> and <hi>aſſiſted their Beginnings,</hi> than <hi>hinder'd</hi> them from <hi>Riſing.</hi> The two other Falſities are, the <hi>ill ſucceſs of the Play,</hi> and <hi>my diſowning it.</hi> The former is manifeſtly without <hi>Foundation;</hi> for it <hi>ſucceeded</hi> beyond my very <hi>hopes,</hi> having been frequently Acted, and never without a conſiderable Audience: And then 'tis a thouſand to one, that having <hi>no ground,</hi> to <hi>diſown</hi> it, I did not <hi>diſown</hi> it; but the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> to a <hi>Nut-ſhell</hi> that I did not <hi>diſown</hi> it for want of <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> when it <hi>ſucceeded</hi> ſo much beyond my <hi>Expectation.</hi> But my malignant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries are the more excuſable, for this courſe method of breaking in upon <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>good Manners,</hi> becauſe it is the only way they have to gratifie the <hi>Genius</hi> and the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Faction together;</hi> and never ſo much pains taken neither, to ſo very, very little purpoſe. They <hi>decry</hi> the <hi>Play,</hi> but in ſuch a manner, that it has the Effect of a <hi>Recommendation.</hi> They call it a <hi>dull Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment;</hi> and that's a dangerous word, I muſt confeſs, from one of the <hi>greatest Maſters</hi> in <hi>humane Nature,</hi> of <hi>that Faculty.</hi> Now I can forgive them this Reproach too, after all the reſt: For this Play does openly diſcover the Original and Root of the Practices and Principles, both of their Party and Cauſe; and they are ſo well acquainted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199796:4"/>with all the Trains and Mazes of Rebellion, that there's nothing new to them in the whole Hiſtory. Or what if it were a little inſipid, there was no Conjuring that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member in <hi>Pope Joan:</hi> And the <hi>Lancaſhire Witches</hi> were without doubt, the moſt <hi>inſipid</hi> Jades that ever flew up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Stage; and yet even <hi>Theſe</hi> by the favour of a <hi>Party</hi> made a ſhift to hold up their heads. Now if we have out-done theſe Plays in their own <hi>dull way,</hi> their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors have ſome ſort of <hi>priviledge</hi> to throw the <hi>first ſtone:</hi> But we ſhall rather chooſe to <hi>yield</hi> the Point of <hi>Dulneſs,</hi> than <hi>contend</hi> for it, againſt ſo indiſputable a Claim.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Matters of State</hi> (it ſeems) <hi>are canvaſſed on the Stage, and things of the Graveſt Concernment there ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged:</hi> And who were the <hi>Aggreſſors,</hi> I beſeech you but a few <hi>factious, popular Hirelings,</hi> that by <hi>tampering</hi> the <hi>Theatres,</hi> and by <hi>poyſoning</hi> the <hi>People,</hi> made a <hi>Play-houſe</hi> more Seditious than a <hi>Conventicle:</hi> So that the <hi>Loyal Party</hi> crave only the ſame freedom of <hi>defending</hi> the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> which the other took before-hand of <hi>expoſing</hi> and <hi>defaming</hi> it. There was no complaint of any <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders</hi> of the <hi>Stage</hi> in the Busſle, that was made (even to the <hi>forming</hi> of a <hi>Party</hi>) to uphold a <hi>Farce</hi> of <hi>Theirs.</hi> Upon the Firſt day, the whole Faction (in a manner) appeared; but after One ſight of it, they ſent their <hi>Proxies</hi> of <hi>Serving-men</hi> and <hi>Porters</hi> to <hi>Clap</hi> in the Right of their Patrons: And it was impoſſible ever to have gotten off the <hi>Nonſence</hi> of <hi>three hours</hi> for <hi>Half a Crown,</hi> but for the Providence of ſo <hi>Congruous</hi> an <hi>Audience.</hi> Thus far, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, the <hi>Reckoning</hi> is even, for <hi>Bad Plays,</hi> on <hi>Both Sides;</hi> and for <hi>Plays</hi> written for a <hi>Party.</hi> I ſhall ſay nothing of <hi>their Poets Affection</hi> to the <hi>Government,</hi> unleſs upon an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> and an <hi>odious neceſſity.</hi> But to return to the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Parallel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſaid enough already to convince any man of common ſenſe, That there neither <hi>was,</hi> nor could be any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199796:5"/>
               <hi>Parallel intended:</hi> And it will farther appear, from the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>Subject;</hi> there being no <hi>Relation</hi> betwixt <hi>Henry the Third</hi> and the <hi>Duke of Guiſe,</hi> except that of the <hi>Kings</hi> marrying into the Family of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> If a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon had been deſign'd, how eaſie had it been either to have found a Story, or to have invented one, where the tyes of nature had been nearer? If we conſider their <hi>Actions</hi> or their <hi>Perſons,</hi> a much leſs proportion will be yet found betwixt them: and if we bate the <hi>Popularity,</hi> perhaps none at all. If we conſider them in reference to their <hi>Parties;</hi> the <hi>One</hi> was manifeſtly the <hi>Leader,</hi> the <hi>Other,</hi> at the worſt, is but <hi>miſled.</hi> The <hi>Deſigns</hi> of the <hi>One</hi> tended openly to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation:</hi> thoſe of the <hi>Other</hi> may yet be interpreted more fairly; and I hope from the natural candour and probity of his temper, that it will come to a perfect ſubmiſſion and reconcilement at laſt. But that which perfectly deſtroys this <hi>pretended Parallel,</hi> is that <hi>our</hi> Picture of the <hi>Duke of Guiſe</hi> is exactly accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Original</hi> in the <hi>History;</hi> his Actions, his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; nay, ſometimes his very Words, are ſo juſtly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, that whoever has read him in <hi>Davila,</hi> ſees him the ſame here. There is no going out of the way, no daſh of a Pen to make any <hi>By-feature</hi> reſemble him to any other Man: and indeed, excepting his Ambition, there was not in <hi>France,</hi> or perhaps in any other Country, any man of his Age vain enough to hope he cou'd be miſtaken for him. So that if we <hi>Wou'd</hi> have made a <hi>Parallel,</hi> we <hi>Cou'd</hi> not. And yet I fancy, that where I make it my buſineſs to draw <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> It will be no hard matter to judg who ſate for the <hi>Picture.</hi> For the <hi>Duke of Guiſes return to Paris contrary to the Kings Order,</hi> enough al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready has been ſaid; 'Twas too conſiderable in the Story to be omitted, becauſe it occaſion'd the miſchiefs that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued: But in <hi>this likeneſs</hi> which was only <hi>Caſual,</hi> no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger follow'd. I am confident there was none intended; and am ſatisfied that none was fear'd. But the Argument
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199796:5"/>drawn from our evident deſign is yet, if poſſible, more convincing. The firſt words of the <hi>Prologue</hi> ſpake the <hi>Play</hi> to be a <hi>Parallel,</hi> and then you are immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd how far that <hi>Parallel</hi> extended, and of what it is ſo. <hi>The Holy League begot the Covenant, Guiſards got the Whig, &amp;c.</hi> So then it is not, (as the ſharling Authors of the <hi>Reflections</hi> tell you) a Parallel of the <hi>Men,</hi> but of the <hi>Times.</hi> A Parallel of the <hi>Factions,</hi> and of the <hi>Leaguers.</hi> And every one knows that this Prologue was written before the ſtopping of the Play. Neither was the name alter'd on any ſuch account as they inſinuate, but laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide long before, becauſe a Book call'd the <hi>Parallel</hi> had been printed, reſembling the <hi>French League,</hi> to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Covenant;</hi> and therefore we thought it not conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to make uſe of another mans Title. The <hi>chief perſon</hi> in the <hi>Tragedy,</hi> or He whoſe <hi>diſaſters</hi> are the <hi>Subject</hi> of it, may in reaſon give the Name; and ſo it was call'd the <hi>Duke of Guiſe.</hi> Our intention therefore was to make the Play a Parallel, betwixt the <hi>Holy League</hi> plotted by the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and its <hi>Adhaerents,</hi> with the <hi>Covenant</hi> plotted by the <hi>Rebels</hi> in the time of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>new Aſſociation,</hi> which was the Spawn of the <hi>old Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>This Parallel</hi> is plain, that the <hi>Excluſion</hi> of the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Heir</hi> was the main deſign of <hi>Both Parties:</hi> and that the endeavours to get the <hi>Lieutenancy</hi> of <hi>France</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed on the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>League,</hi> is in effect the ſame with offering to get the <hi>Militia</hi> out of the <hi>Kings hands</hi> (as declar'd by Parliament) and conſequently that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Peace and War ſhould be wholly in the People. 'Tis alſo true that the <hi>Tumults</hi> in the <hi>City,</hi> in the choice of their <hi>Officers</hi> have had no ſmall reſemblance with a <hi>Pariſian Rabble.</hi> And I am afraid that both <hi>Their Faction</hi> and <hi>Ours</hi> had the <hi>ſame Good Lord.</hi> I believe alſo that if <hi>Julian</hi> had been written and calculated for the <hi>Pariſians,</hi> as it was for <hi>our Sectaries,</hi> one of <hi>their Sheriffs</hi> might have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199796:6"/>miſtaken too, and call'd him <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I need not puſh this Point any further, where the <hi>Parallel</hi> was intended, I am certain it will reach: But a larger account of the Proceedings in the City may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from a better hand, and I have no reaſon to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall it. In the mean time, becauſe there has been no <hi>Actual Rebellion,</hi> the Faction triumph in their <hi>Loyalty;</hi> which if it were out of <hi>Principle,</hi> all our diviſions would ſoon be ended, and we the happy People, which God and the Conſtitution of our Government have put us in condition to be: but ſo long as they take it for a <hi>Maxim,</hi> that the <hi>King</hi> is but an <hi>Officer in Truſt,</hi> that the <hi>People,</hi> or their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> are <hi>ſuperiour</hi> to him, Judges of <hi>Miſcarriages,</hi> and have power of <hi>Revocation,</hi> 'tis a plain caſe, that when ever they pleaſe they may take up arms; and, according to <hi>Their</hi> Doctrine, <hi>lawfully</hi> too. Let them joyntly renounce this one opinion, as in Conſcience and Law they are bound to do, becauſe both Scripture and Acts of Parliament oblige them to it, and we will then thank their <hi>Obedience</hi> for our quiet, whereas now we are only beholding to them for their <hi>Fear.</hi> The miſeries of the laſt War are yet too freſh in all mens memory: and they are <hi>not</hi> Rebels only becauſe they have been ſo <hi>too lately.</hi> An Author of theirs has told us roundly the <hi>Weſt-Country Proverb; Chad eat more Cheeſe and chad it:</hi> Their Stomach is as good as ever it was; but the miſchief on't is, they are either <hi>Muzled</hi> or want their <hi>Teeth.</hi> If there were as many <hi>Fanatiques</hi> now in <hi>England,</hi> as there were <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the <hi>Empire,</hi> when <hi>Julian</hi> reign'd, I doubt we ſhould not find them much enclin'd to <hi>paſſive obedience;</hi> and <hi>Curſe ye Meroz</hi> wou'd be oftner preach'd upon, than <hi>Give to Caeſar,</hi> except in the ſenſe <hi>Mr. Hunt</hi> means it.</p>
            <p>Having clearly ſhown wherein the <hi>Parallel</hi> conſiſted, which no man can miſtake, who does not wilfully; I need not juſtifie my ſelf, in what concerns the ſacred Perſon of his Majeſty. Neither the <hi>French Hiſtory,</hi> nor our own
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199796:6"/>could have ſupplied me, nor <hi>Plutarch</hi> himſelf, were he now alive, could have found a <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> to have compared to him, in that eminent vertue of his <hi>Clemency;</hi> even his enemies muſt acknowledge it to be <hi>Superlative,</hi> becauſe they live by it. Far be it from flattery, if I ſay, that there is nothing under Heaven, which can furniſh me with a <hi>Parallel;</hi> and that in his <hi>Mercy,</hi> he is of all men the <hi>Trueſt Image</hi> of his <hi>Maker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry the Third</hi> was a Prince of a <hi>mix'd Character;</hi> he had, as an old <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſays of another, <hi>Magnas virtutes, nec minora vitia:</hi> but amongſt thoſe vertues, I do not find his <hi>forgiving qualities</hi> to be much celebrated. That he was deeply engag'd in the bloody <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>St. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew,</hi> is notoriouſly known: and if the relation print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Memoires of Villeroy</hi> be true, he confeſſes there that the <hi>Admiral</hi> having brought him and the Queen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into ſuſpition with his Brother then reigning, for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to leſſen his Authority, and draw it to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, he firſt deſign'd his Accuſers death by <hi>Maurevel,</hi> who ſhot him with a <hi>Carabine,</hi> but fail'd to kill him; after which, he puſh'd on the <hi>King</hi> to that <hi>dreadful Revenge,</hi> which immediately ſucceeded. 'Tis true, the Provocations were high, there had been reiterated Rebellions, but a Peace was now concluded; it was ſolemnly <hi>Sworn</hi> to by <hi>both Parties,</hi> and as great an aſſurance of <hi>Safety,</hi> given to the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as the <hi>Word of a King and Publick Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> could make it. Therefore the Puniſhment was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable, and it pleaſ'd God, (if we may dare to judge of his ſecret Providence) to cut off that King in the very flower of his Youth, to blaſt his Succeſſor in his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, to raiſe againſt him the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotter and Executioner of that inhumane Action (who by the Divine Juſtice, fell afterwards into the ſame ſnare which he had laid for others) and finally, to dye a violent Death himſelf; murder'd by a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> an <hi>Enthuſiast</hi> of <hi>his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199796:7"/>own Religion.</hi> From theſe Premiſſes, let it be concluded. if reaſonably it can, that we could draw a <hi>Parallel,</hi> where the lines were ſo diametrically oppoſite. We were indeed obliged by the Laws of Poetry, to caſt into <hi>Shadows</hi> the <hi>vices</hi> of this <hi>Prince;</hi> for an Excellent Critique has lately told us, that <hi>when a KING is nam'd, a HEROE is ſuppoſ'd:</hi> 'Tis a reverence due to Majeſty, to make the Vertues as conſpicuous, and the Vices as obſcure as we can poſſibly. And this we own, we have either perform'd, or at leaſt endeavour'd. But if we were more favourable to that Character than the exactneſs of Hiſtory would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, we have been far from diminiſhing a <hi>Greater,</hi> by drawing it into compariſon. You may ſee through the whole conduct of the Play, a <hi>King</hi> naturally <hi>ſevere,</hi> and a <hi>reſolution</hi> carried on to <hi>revenge</hi> himſelf to the uttermoſt on the <hi>Rebellious Conſpirators.</hi> That this was ſometimes ſhaken by reaſons of policy and pity, is confeſſ'd; but it always return'd with greater force, and ended at laſt in the ruine of his Enemies. In the mean time, we cannot but obſerve the wonderful Loyalty on the <hi>other</hi> Side; that the <hi>Play</hi> was to be ſtopp'd, becauſe the <hi>King</hi> was <hi>repreſented.</hi> May we have many ſuch proofs of their Duty and reſpect: but there was no occaſion for them here. 'Tis to be ſuppoſ'd, that his Majeſty himſelf was made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this objection; if he were ſo, he was the ſupream and only Judg of it; and then the Event juſtifies us: If it were inſpected only by thoſe whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, 'tis hard if his own Officers and Servants ſhould not ſee as much ill in it as other men, and be as willing to prevent it; eſpecially when there was no ſollicitation uſ'd to have it acted. 'Tis known that noble perſon to whom it was referr'd, is a ſevere Critique on good Senſe, Decency, and Morality; and I can aſſure the World, that the Rules of <hi>Horace</hi> are more familiar to <hi>him,</hi> than they are to <hi>me.</hi> He remembers too well that the <hi>vetus Comae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> was baniſh'd from the <hi>Athenian Theatre</hi> for its too
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199796:7"/>much licence in repreſenting perſons, and would never have pardon'd it in this or any Play.</p>
            <p>What opinion <hi>Henry the Third</hi> had of his <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> is evident from the words he ſpoke upon his <hi>Death-bed: He exhorted the Nobility</hi> (ſays <hi>Davila</hi>) <hi>to acknowledge the King of</hi> Navarre, <hi>to whom the Kingdom of right belong'd; and that they ſhould not ſtick at the difference of Religion: for both the King of</hi> Navarre, <hi>a man of a ſincere noble na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, would in the end return into the boſom of the Church, and the Pope being better inform'd, would receive him into his favour to prevent the ruine of the whole Kingdom.</hi> I hope I ſhall not need in this Quotation to defend my ſelf. as if it were my opinion, that the Pope has any right to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Kingdoms: my meaning is evident, that the Kings judgment of his Brother-in-law, was the ſame which I have copied: and I muſt farther add from <hi>Davila,</hi> that the Arguments I have uſed in defence of that <hi>Succeſsion,</hi> were chiefly drawn from the King's anſwer to the Deputies, as they may be ſeen more at large in page 730. and 731. of the firſt Edition of that Hiſtory in <hi>Engliſh:</hi> There the three Eſtates, to the wonder of all men joyntly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd in cutting off the <hi>Succeſſion;</hi> the Clergy, who were manag'd by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> and Cardinal of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> were the firſt who promoted it; and the Commons and Nobility afterwards conſented, as referring themſelves (ſays our Author) to the <hi>Clergy;</hi> ſo that there was only the <hi>King</hi> to ſtand in the Gap; and he by artifice diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Storm which was breaking upon Poſterity.</p>
            <p>The Crown was then reduced to the loweſt Ebb of its Authority; and the King, in a manner, ſtood ſingle, and yet preſerv'd his <hi>Negative entire:</hi> but if the Clergy and Nobility had been on his part of the Ballance, it might reaſonably be ſuppoſ'd, that the meeting of thoſe Eſtates at <hi>Blois,</hi> had heal'd the breaches of the Nation; and not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199796:8"/>forc'd him to the <hi>ratio ultima Regum,</hi> which is never to be <hi>praiſ'd,</hi> nor is it here, but only <hi>excuſ'd</hi> as the laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of his neceſſity. As for the <hi>Parallel</hi> betwixt the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and any other Prince now living, what like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the God of Nature, and the deſcent of Vertues in the ſame channel have produced, is evident; I have only to ſay that the Nation certainly is happy where the Royal Vertues of the Progenitors are deriv'd on their Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants.</p>
            <p>In that Scene, 'tis true, there is but <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>Three Estates mention'd;</hi> but the <hi>Other two</hi> are virtually <hi>inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;</hi> for the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> and <hi>Cardinal</hi> are at the head of the <hi>Deputies:</hi> and that the <hi>reſt</hi> are <hi>mute perſons,</hi> every Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique underſtands the reaſon, <hi>ne quarta loqui perſona labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boret;</hi> I am never willing to cumber the Stage with many Speakers, when I can reaſonably avoid it; as here I might. And what if I had a mind to paſs over the Clergy and Nobility of <hi>France</hi> in ſilence, and to excuſe them from joyning in ſo <hi>illegal</hi> and ſo <hi>ungodly</hi> a <hi>Decree?</hi> Am I ty'd in <hi>Poetry,</hi> to the ſtrict rules of <hi>Hiſtory?</hi> I have follow'd it in this Play more cloſely, than ſuited with the Laws of the <hi>Drama,</hi> and a great Victory they will have, who ſhall diſcover to the World this wonderful Secret, that I have not obſerv'd the Unities of <hi>place</hi> and <hi>time;</hi> but are they better kept in the <hi>Farce</hi> of the <hi>Libertine destroy'd?</hi> 'Twas our common buſineſs here to draw the <hi>Parallel</hi> of the Times, and not to make an <hi>Exact Tragedy:</hi> For this once we were reſolv'd to erre with honeſt <hi>Shakeſpear:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can <hi>Catiline</hi> or <hi>Sejanus,</hi> (written by the great Maſter of our Art) ſtand excuſ'd any more than we, from this exception: but if <hi>we</hi> muſt be <hi>criticiſ'd,</hi> ſome Plays of our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> may be expoſ'd, and let them reckon their gains vvhen the diſpute is ended. I am accuſ'd of <hi>ignorance,</hi> for ſpeaking of the <hi>Third Eſtate,</hi> as <hi>not ſitting in the ſame Houſe with the other two:</hi> Let not thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199796:8"/>miſtake themſelves, there are many things in <hi>Plays</hi> to be accommodated to the Country in vvhich vve live; I ſpoke to the underſtanding of an <hi>Engliſh Audience; Our three Eſtates</hi> novv ſit, and have long done ſo in <hi>Two Houſes;</hi> but our <hi>Records</hi> bear witneſs, that they, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>French Custom,</hi> have ſate in one; that is the <hi>Lords Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal within</hi> the <hi>Barr,</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi> without it. If that Cuſtom had been ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued here, it ſhould have been ſo repreſented; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe, I was forc'd to write ſo as to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by our own Country-men. If theſe be Errours, a <hi>Bigger</hi> Poet than either of us two has fallen into greater, and the Proofs are ready, whenever the Suit ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commenc'd.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> the <hi>Jehu</hi> of the Party, begins very furiouſly with me, and ſays I have already <hi>condemn'd the Charter and City,</hi> and have <hi>executed the Magistrates in Effigie upon the Stage, in a Play call'd the</hi> Duke of Guiſe, <hi>frequently acted, and applauded, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compare the latter end of this Sentence with what the <hi>Two Authors of the Reflections,</hi> or perhaps the <hi>Aſſociating Clubb</hi> of the <hi>Devil-Tavern</hi> write in the beginning of their Libel. <hi>Never was Mountain deliver'd of ſuch a Mouſe; the fierceſt Tories have been aſham'd to defend this Piece: they who have any ſparks of wit among them are ſo true to their pleaſure, that they will not ſuffer dulneſs to paſs upon them for wit, nor tediouſneſs for diverſion: which is the reaſon that this Piece has not met with the expected applauſe: I never ſaw a Play more deficient in Wit, good Characters or Entertainment, than this is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For ſhame, Gentlemen, pack your Evidence a little better againſt another time: You ſee, <hi>My Lord Chief Baron,</hi> has delivered his Opinion, that <hi>the Play was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199796:9"/>acted and applauded;</hi> but you of the <hi>Jury,</hi> have found <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> on the <hi>Wit</hi> and the <hi>Succeſs</hi> of it. <hi>Oates, Dugdale</hi> and <hi>Turbervile,</hi> never diſagreed <hi>more</hi> than you do; let us know at laſt, which of the Witneſſes are <hi>true Proteſtants,</hi> and which are <hi>Iriſh.</hi> But it ſeems your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors had contrary Deſigns: Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> thought fit to ſay, it was <hi>frequently acted and applauded, becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>it was intended to provoke the Rabble into Tumults and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order.</hi> Now if it were not ſeen frequently, this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would loſe ſomewhat of its force; the <hi>Reflectors</hi> buſineſs went another way, it was to be allow'd <hi>no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, no Succeſs,</hi> but to be damn'd Root and Branch, to prevent the Prejudice it might do their Party; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, as much as in them lay, they have drawn a Bill of <hi>Excluſion</hi> for it on the <hi>Stage;</hi> But what <hi>Rabble</hi> was it to provoke? Are the <hi>Audience</hi> of a <hi>Play-houſe</hi> (which are generally Perſons of Honour, Noblemen and Ladies, or at worſt, as one of your Authors calls his Gallants, <hi>Men of Wit and Pleaſure about the Town</hi>) are <hi>theſe</hi> the <hi>Rabble</hi> of Mr. <hi>Hunt?</hi> I have ſeen a <hi>Rabble</hi> at Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfreys</hi> Night, and have heard of ſuch a name, at <hi>true Proteſtant Meeting-houſes;</hi> but a <hi>Rabble</hi> is not to be provoked, where it never comes. Indeed, we had one in this Tragedy, but it was upon the <hi>Stage;</hi> and that's the Reaſon, why your <hi>Reflectors</hi> would break the Glaſs, which has ſhewed them their own Faces. The buſineſs of the <hi>Theatre,</hi> is to expoſe <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Folly;</hi> to diſſwade men by Examples from one, and to ſhame them out of the other. And however you may pervert our good intentions, it was here particularly to reduce men to Loyalty, by ſhewing the pernicious conſequences of Rebellion, and Popular Inſurrections. I believe no man, who loves the Government, would be glad, to ſee the <hi>Rabble</hi> in ſuch a poſture, as they were repreſented in our Play: But if the <hi>Tragedy</hi> had ended, on <hi>your ſide,</hi> the <hi>Play</hi> had been a <hi>Loyal Witty Poem,</hi> the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199796:9"/>of it, ſhould have been recorded by immortal <hi>Og</hi> or <hi>Doeg,</hi> and the <hi>Rabble Scene,</hi> ſhould have been <hi>true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> though a <hi>Whig Devil</hi> were at the <hi>Head</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, pray, where lies the Relation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Tragedy of the Duke of Guiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Charter of London?</hi> Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> has found a rare connexion, for he tacks them together, by the kicking of the <hi>Sheriffs:</hi> That Chain of thought was a little ominous, for ſomething like a kicking, has ſucceeded the Printing of his <hi>Book;</hi> and the <hi>Charter of London</hi> was the <hi>Quarrel.</hi> For my part, I have not Law enough to ſtate that queſtion, much leſs decide it; let the <hi>Charter</hi> ſhift for it ſelf in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter Hall,</hi> the Government is ſomewhat wiſer, than to imploy my ignorance on ſuch a Subject; my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to honeſt <hi>Nat. Lee,</hi> was the only Bribe I had, to ingage me in this trouble; for which, he has the good fortune to eſcape <hi>Scot-free,</hi> and I am left in pawn for the Reckoning, who had the leaſt ſhare in the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But the Riſing, it ſeems, ſhould have been on the <hi>true Proteſtants ſide, for he has tryed,</hi> ſays ingenious Mr. <hi>Hunt, what he could do, towards making the Charter forfeitable, by ſome Extravagancy and Diſorder of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> A wiſe man I had been doubtleſs for my pains, to raiſe the <hi>Rabble</hi> to a <hi>Tumult,</hi> where I had been certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, one of the firſt men, whom they had <hi>limn'd</hi> or <hi>drag'd</hi> to the next convenient <hi>Sign-Poſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But on ſecond thought, he ſays, this ought not to move the Citizens: he is much in the right; for the <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Scene</hi> was written on purpoſe, to keep his Party of them in the bounds of <hi>Duty.</hi> 'Tis the buſineſs of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men to ſtir up the Populace: Sir <hi>Edmond on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back,</hi> attended by a <hi>Swindging Pope in Effigie, and forty thouſand true Proteſtants</hi> for his Guard to Execution, are a Show more proper for that deſign, than a <hi>thou ſand Stage-Plays.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199796:10"/>
            <p>Well, he has fortified his Opinion with a Reaſon, however, why the People ſhould not be moved; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have ſo maliciouſly and miſchievouſly repreſented the King, and the Kings Son; nay, and his Favourite</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Duke too; to whom I give the worſt ſtrokes of my unlucky Fancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This need not be anſwered, for 'tis already manifeſt, that neither the King, nor the Kings Son are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, neither that Son, he means, nor any of the reſt, God bleſs them all. What ſtrokes of my unlucky Fancy, I have given to his Royal Highneſs, will be ſeen, and it will be ſeen alſo, who ſtrikes him worſt and moſt unluckily.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duke of Guiſe,</hi> he tells us, <hi>ought to have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented a great Prince, that had inſerv'd to ſome moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Villany, to pleaſe the Rage or Luſt of a Tyrant; ſuch great Courtiers have been often ſacrificed, to appeaſe the Furies of the Tyrants guilty Conſcience; to expiate for his Sin, and to attone the People. For a Tyrant naturally ſtands in fear of ſuch wicked Miniſters, is obnoxious to them, aw'd by them, and they drag him to greater evils, for their own impunity, than they perpetrated for his Pleaſure, and their own Ambition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure, he ſaid not all this for nothing, I would know of him, on what perſons he would fix the Sting of this ſharp Satyr? <hi>What two</hi> they are, whom, to uſe his own Words, he <hi>ſo maliciouſly and miſchievouſly would repreſent?</hi> For my part, I dare not underſtand the villany of his meaning; but ſome body was to have been ſhown a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and ſome other <hi>a great Prince, inſerving to ſome deteſtable Villany, and to that Tyrants Rage and Luſt;</hi> this great <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Courtier</hi> ought to be <hi>ſacrificed,</hi> to attone the <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>Tyrant</hi> is perſwaded, for his own intereſt, to give him up to <hi>publick Justice.</hi> I ſay
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199796:10"/>no more, but that he has ſtudied the Law to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. He is dancing on the Rope without a <hi>Metaphor,</hi> his knowledge of the Law is the Staff that poizes him, and ſaves his Neck. The <hi>Party</hi> indeed ſpeaks out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, for wickedneſs is not always ſo wiſe, as to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, eſpecially when it is driven to deſpair. By ſome of their Diſcourſes, we may gueſs at whom he points; but he has fenc'd himſelf in with ſo many Evaſions, that he is ſafe in his Sacriledge; and he who dares to anſwer him, may become obnoxious. 'Tis true, he breaks a little out of the Clouds, within two Paragraphs; for there he tells you, that <hi>Caius Caeſar (to give unto</hi> Caeſar, <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſars) <hi>was in the</hi> Catiline Conſpiracy; a fine inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation this, to be ſneer'd at by his Party, and yet not to be taken hold of by <hi>publick Juſtice:</hi> They would be glad now, that I or any man, ſhould bolt out their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Treaſon for them: for their loop hole is ready, that the <hi>Caeſar</hi> here ſpoken of, was a private man. But the application of the Text, declares the Authors to be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Caeſar,</hi> which is ſo black and ſo infamous an aſperſion, that nothing leſs than the higheſt clemency can leave it unpuniſh'd. I cou'd reflect on his ignorance in this place, for attributing theſe words to <hi>Caeſar, he that is not with us, is againſt us:</hi> He ſeems to have miſtaken them, out of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and that's the beſt defence I can make for him; for if he did it knowingly, 'twas impiouſly done, to put our <hi>Saviours words</hi> into <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s mouth. But <hi>His Law</hi> and <hi>Our Goſpel,</hi> are <hi>two things;</hi> this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's <hi>Knowledge</hi> is not of the <hi>Bible,</hi> any more than his <hi>Practice</hi> is <hi>according</hi> to it. He tells you, he will give the world a taſt of my <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Impiety;</hi> for which he quotes theſe following Verſes, in the ſecond or third Act of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>For Conſcience or Heavens fear, religious Rules</l>
               <l>Are all State-bells to toll in pious Fools.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:199796:11"/>
            <p>In the firſt place, he is miſtaken in his <hi>Man,</hi> for the Verſes are not <hi>mine,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Lees:</hi> I ask'd him concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and have this account, that they were ſpoken by the <hi>Devil;</hi> now, what can either <hi>Whig</hi> or <hi>Devil</hi> ſay, more proper to their <hi>Character,</hi> than that <hi>Religion</hi> is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Name,</hi> a <hi>Stalking horſe,</hi> as errant a <hi>Property</hi> as <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Property themſelves</hi> are amongſt <hi>their Party?</hi> yet for theſe two lines, which in the mouth that ſpeaks them, are of no offence, he hallooes on the whole pack, againſt me: <hi>Judge, Juſtice, Surrogate,</hi> and <hi>Official</hi> are to be employed, at his Suit, to direct <hi>Proceſs,</hi> and boring through the <hi>Tongue</hi> for <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> is the leaſt Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his <hi>Charity</hi> will allow me.</p>
            <p>I find 'tis happy for me, that he was not made a <hi>Judge,</hi> and yet I had as lieve have him my <hi>Judge</hi> as my Council, if my Life were at ſtake. My poor Lord <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> was well helpt up with this Gentleman for his Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; no doubt, he gave that unfortunate Nobleman, moſt admirable advice toward the <hi>Saving</hi> of his life; and would have rejoyc'd exceedingly, to have ſeen him clear'd. I think, I have diſprov'd his inſtance of my <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> it remains for him, to juſtifie <hi>his Religion,</hi> in putting the words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> into a <hi>Heathens</hi> mouth: and much more in his prophane alluſion to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> in the other Text; <hi>Give unto</hi> Caeſar, <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſars; which, if it be not a profanation of the Bible, for the ſake of a <hi>ſilly Witticiſm,</hi> let all men, but his own Party judge. I am not malicious enough to return him the names which he has call'd me; but of all ſins, I thank God, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways abhor'd <hi>Atheiſm:</hi> and I had need be a <hi>better Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> than Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> has ſhown himſelf, if I forgive him ſo infamous a <hi>Slander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as he has miſtaken <hi>our Saviour</hi> for <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> ſo he would <hi>Pompey</hi> too, if he were let alone: to him, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199796:11"/>to his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or to the like Cauſe it belong'd, he ſays, to uſe theſe words, <hi>he that is not with us is againſt us.</hi> I find he cares not whoſe the Expreſſion is, ſo it be not Chriſts. But how comes <hi>Pompey the Great</hi> to be a <hi>Whig?</hi> He was indeed, a Defender of the ancient eſtabliſh'd <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Government;</hi> but <hi>Caeſar</hi> was the <hi>Whig,</hi> who took up Arms unlawfully to <hi>ſubvert</hi> it. Our <hi>Liberties</hi> and our <hi>Religion</hi> both are ſafe, they are ſecur'd to us by the <hi>Laws,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> are executed under an <hi>eſtabliſh'd Government,</hi> by a <hi>Lawful King.</hi> The <hi>Defender</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> is the <hi>Defender</hi> of our <hi>Common Freedom;</hi> to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> to <hi>Write,</hi> to <hi>Rail</hi> againſt this Adminiſtration, are all <hi>Endeavours</hi> to deſtroy the <hi>Government,</hi> and to oppoſe the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> in any private man, is a <hi>Treaſonable Pactice</hi> againſt the <hi>Foundation</hi> of it. <hi>Pompey</hi> very honourably maintain'd the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his Country, which was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by a <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> So that there lies no <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel</hi> betwixt his <hi>Cauſe</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hunts,</hi> except in the bare notion of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as it is oppoſ'd to <hi>Monarchy:</hi> and that's the thing he would obliquely ſlur upon us. Yet on theſe Premiſſes, he is for ordering my <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice,</hi> to grant out <hi>Warrants</hi> againſt all thoſe who have <hi>applauded the Duke of Guiſe;</hi> as if they committed a <hi>Riot</hi> when they <hi>Clapp'd:</hi> I ſuppoſe they paid for their Places, as well as he and his Party did, who Hiſs'd. If he were not <hi>half Diſtracted,</hi> for not being <hi>Lord Chief Baron,</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks he ſhould be Lawyer enough, to adviſe my Lord Chief Juſtice better. To <hi>Clap</hi> and <hi>Hiſs</hi> are the Priviledges of a <hi>Free-born Subject</hi> in a <hi>Play-houſe:</hi> they buy them with their Money, and their Hands and Mouths are their own Property: It belongs to the <hi>Maſter of the Revels,</hi> to ſee that no <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Immorality</hi> be in the <hi>Play;</hi> but when 'tis <hi>acted,</hi> let every man like or diſlike freely: not but that reſpect ſhould be us'd too, in the preſence of the King, for by his <hi>Permiſſion</hi> the <hi>Actors</hi> are allow'd: 'Tis due to his <hi>Perſon,</hi> as he is <hi>Sacred,</hi> and to the Succeſſors, as being
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199796:12"/>next related to him: there are opportunities enow for men to hiſs, who are ſo diſpoſ'd, in their abſence: for when the King is in ſight, though but by accident, a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor is repriev'd from death: Yet ſuch is the Duty, and good manners of theſe good Subjects, that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore not ſome rudeneſs in his Majeſties preſence; but when his Royal Highneſs and his Court were only there, they puſh'd it as far as their malice had power; and if their Party had been more numerous, the Affront had been greater.</p>
            <p>The next Paragraph of our Authors, is a Panegyrique on the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> which concerns not me, who am very far from detracting from him: the Obligations I have had to him, were thoſe, of his Countenance, his Favour, his good Word, and his Eſteem; all which I have likewiſe had in a greater meaſure from his excellent Dutcheſs, the Patroneſs of my poor unworthy Poetry. If I had not greater, the fault was never in their want of goodneſs to me, but in my own backwardneſs to ask, which has allways, and I believe will ever keep me from riſing in the World. Let this be enough, with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men, to clear me from the imputation of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful man, with which my enemies have moſt unjuſtly tax'd me. If I am a mercenary Scribler, the Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Treaſury beſt know: I am ſure, they have found me no importunate Solicitor: for I know my ſelf, I deſerv'd little, and therefore have never deſir'd much. I return that ſlander with juſt diſdain on my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers; 'tis for men who have ill Conſciences to ſuſpect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: I am reſolv'd to ſtand or fall with the Cauſe of God, my King and Country; never to trouble my ſelf for any railing aſperſions which I have not deſerv'd, and to leave it as a Portion to my Children, that they had a Father, who durſt do his duty, and was neither Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous nor Mercenary.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199796:12"/>
            <p>As little am I concern'd at that imputation of my back friends, that I have confeſs'd my ſelf to be put on to write as I do: If they mean this Play in particular, that is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly prov'd againſt them to be falſe: For the reſt of my Writings, my hatred of their Practiſes and Principles, was cauſe enough to expoſe them, as I have done, and will do more. I do not think as they do; for if I did, I muſt think <hi>Treaſon:</hi> But I muſt in conſcence write as I do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I <hi>know,</hi> which is more than <hi>thinking,</hi> that I write for a <hi>lawful eſtabliſh'd Government</hi> againſt <hi>Anarchy, Innovation,</hi> and <hi>Sedition:</hi> But <hi>theſe Lyes</hi> (as Prince <hi>Harry</hi> ſaid to <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe) are as groſs as he that made them.</hi> More I need not ſay, for I am accuſ'd without witneſs. I fear not any of their <hi>Evidences;</hi> not even him of <hi>Salamanca;</hi> who though he has diſown'd his <hi>Doctorſhip</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> yet there are ſome allow him to have taken a certain <hi>degree</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi> a Climate they ſay more proper for his <hi>Maſculine Conſtitution.</hi> To conclude this ridiculous Accuſation againſt me, I know but four men in their whole Party to whom I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for above this year laſt paſt; and with them neither but caſually and curſorily. We have been acquaintance of a long ſtanding, many years before this accurſed Plot divided men into ſeveral Parties: I dare call them to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whether the moſt I have at any time ſaid, will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to more than this, that <hi>I hop'd the time would come when theſe names of</hi> Whig <hi>and</hi> Tory <hi>would ceaſe among us; and that we might live together, as we had done formerly.</hi> I have ſince this Pamphet met accidentally with two of them; and I am ſure they are ſo far from being my Accuſers, that they have ſeverally own'd to me, that all men who eſpouſe a Party, muſt expect to blacken'd by the contrary Side: that themſelves knew nothing of it, nor of the <hi>Authors</hi> of the <hi>Reflections.</hi> It remains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be conſider'd, whether, if I were as much a <hi>Knave</hi> as they wou'd make me, I am <hi>Fool</hi> enough to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199796:13"/>of this Charge: and whether they who raiſ'd it, wou'd have made it publique, if they had thought I was theirs inwardly. For 'tis plain they are glad of worſe Scriblers than I am, and maintain them too, as I could prove, if I envy'd them their miſerable ſubſiſtance. I ſay no more, but let my Actions ſpeak for me: <hi>ſpectemur agendo,</hi> that's the trial.</p>
            <p>Much leſs am I concern'd at the noble name of <hi>Bayes;</hi> that's a <hi>Brat</hi> ſo like his own <hi>Father,</hi> that he cannot be miſtaken for any other body: they might as reaſonably have call'd <hi>Tom Sternhold, Virgil,</hi> and the reſemblance would have held as well.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Knave</hi> and <hi>Sycophant,</hi> and <hi>Raſcal,</hi> and <hi>Impudent,</hi> and <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>old Serpent,</hi> and a thouſand ſuch Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrows, I take them to be only names of Parties: And cou'd return <hi>Murtherer</hi> and <hi>Cheat,</hi> and <hi>Whig-napper,</hi> and <hi>Sodomite;</hi> and in ſhort the goodly number of the <hi>ſeaven deadly Sins,</hi> with all their Kindred and Relations, which are Names of <hi>Parties</hi> too; but <hi>Saints</hi> will be <hi>Saints</hi> in ſpight of Villainy. I believe they wou'd paſs themſelves upon us for ſuch a <hi>Compound</hi> as <hi>Mithridate,</hi> or <hi>Venice-Treacle;</hi> as if Whiggiſm were an admirable <hi>Cordial</hi> in the <hi>Maſs,</hi> though the ſeveral <hi>Ingredients</hi> are ranck <hi>Poyſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if I think either Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> a <hi>Villain,</hi> or know any of my <hi>Reflectors</hi> to be <hi>ungrateful Rogues,</hi> I do not owe them ſo much kindneſs as to call them ſo; for I am ſatisfied that to prove them either, would but recommend them to their own Party. Yet if ſome will needs make a <hi>merit</hi> of their <hi>infamy,</hi> and provoke a <hi>Legend</hi> of their <hi>ſordid lives,</hi> I think they muſt be gratify'd at laſt; and though I will not take the <hi>Scavengers</hi> employment from him, yet I may be perſwaded to <hi>point</hi> at ſome mens doors, who have heaps of filth before them. But this muſt be when
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199796:13"/>they have a little anger'd me; for hitherto I am provok'd no further than to ſmile at them. And indeed, to look upon the whole Faction in a lump, never was a more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſight than to behold theſe builders of a new <hi>Babel,</hi> how ridiculouſly they are mix'd, and what a rare confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion there is amongſt them. One part of them is carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stone and Mortar for the building of a <hi>Meeting-houſe,</hi> another ſort underſtand not that Language; they are for ſnatching away their Work-fellows materials to ſet up a <hi>Bawdy-houſe:</hi> ſome of them <hi>blaſpheme,</hi> and others <hi>pray;</hi> and both I believe with equal godlineſs at bottom: ſome of them are <hi>Atheists,</hi> ſome <hi>Sectaries,</hi> yet <hi>ALL True Proteſtants. Moſt</hi> of them love <hi>all Whores,</hi> but her of <hi>Babylon.</hi> In few words, any man may be what he will, ſo he be one of <hi>Them.</hi> 'Tis enough to deſpiſe the <hi>King,</hi> to hate the <hi>Duke,</hi> and rail at the <hi>Succeſſion:</hi> after this 'tis no matter how a man lives; he is a <hi>Saint</hi> by <hi>infection;</hi> he goes along with the <hi>Party,</hi> has their <hi>mark</hi> upon him; his <hi>wickedneſs</hi> is no more than <hi>frailty; their righteouſneſs</hi> is <hi>imputed</hi> to him: So that as <hi>ignorant rogues</hi> go out <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> when a <hi>Prince</hi> comes to an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> they hope at <hi>the last day,</hi> to take their <hi>Degree</hi> in a Crowd of <hi>True Proteſtants,</hi> and thruſt unheeded into Heaven.</p>
            <p>'Tis a credit to be rayl'd at by ſuch men as theſe. The <hi>Charter-man</hi> in the very <hi>Title-page,</hi> where he hangs out the <hi>Cloth</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> before his Book, gives it for his <hi>Motto, Si populus vult deeipi; decipiatur;</hi> as if he ſhou'd have ſaid, <hi>you have a mind to be couzen'd, and the Devil give you good on't:</hi> If I cry a <hi>Sirreverence,</hi> and you take it for <hi>Honey,</hi> make the beſt of your bargain. For ſhame, good Chriſtians, can you ſuffer ſuch a man to <hi>ſterve,</hi> when you ſee his deſign is upon your <hi>Purſes?</hi> He is contented to expoſe the <hi>Ears repreſentative</hi> of your <hi>Party</hi> on a <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory,</hi> and is in a way of doing you more ſervice than a worn out Witneſs, who can hang no body hereafter but himſelf. He tells you <hi>the Papists clap their hands in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199796:14"/>the hopes they conceive of the ruine of your Government:</hi> does not this <hi>ſingle ſyllable YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R</hi> deſerve a <hi>Pention,</hi> if he can <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> to be <hi>Yours,</hi> and that the <hi>King</hi> has <hi>nothing</hi> to do in <hi>your Republick?</hi> he continues, as if that were as ſure and certain to Them, as it is to Us, without doubt, that they (the <hi>Papiſts</hi>) once fired the City, juſt as certain in your own Conſciences. I wiſh the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts had no more to anſwer for, than that accuſation: pray let it be put to the <hi>Vote,</hi> and reſolv'd upon the <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> by your <hi>whole Party,</hi> that the <hi>North-eaſt Wind,</hi> is not only <hi>ill-affected</hi> to Man and Beaſt, but is alſo a <hi>Tory</hi> or <hi>Tantivy Papiſt</hi> in <hi>Maſquerade.</hi> I am ſatisfy'd, not to have <hi>ſo much art left me as to frame any thing agreeable, or veriſimilar,</hi> but 'tis plain that he has, and therefore, as I ought in juſtice, I reſign my <hi>Laurel,</hi> and my <hi>Bayes</hi> too, to Mr. <hi>Hunt;</hi> 'tis he ſets up for the Poet now; and has the only art to <hi>amuſe</hi> and to <hi>deceive the people.</hi> You may ſee how profound his knowledg is in <hi>Poetry;</hi> for he tells you juſt before, that <hi>my Heroes are commonly ſuch Monſters as</hi> Theſeus <hi>and</hi> Hercules; <hi>renown'd throughout all Ages for deſtroying.</hi> Now <hi>Theſeus</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> you know have been the <hi>Heroes</hi> of <hi>all Poets,</hi> and have been renown'd through all Ages, for <hi>deſtroying Monſters,</hi> for <hi>ſuccouring</hi> the <hi>Distreſt,</hi> and for putting to <hi>death inhumane arbitrary Tyrants.</hi> Is this your <hi>Oracle?</hi> If he were to write the Acts and Monuments of <hi>Whig Heroes,</hi> I find they ſhou'd be quite contrary to mine: <hi>deſtroyers indeed,</hi> but of a <hi>Lawful Government; Murtherers,</hi> but of their <hi>fellow Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; Lovers</hi> as <hi>Hercules</hi> was of <hi>Hylas;</hi> with a journey at laſt to <hi>Hell,</hi> like that of <hi>Theſeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But mark the wiſe Conſequences of our Author. I have not, he ſays, <hi>ſo much art left me to make any thing agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or veriſimilar, wherewith to amuſe or deceive the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> and yet in the very <hi>next Paragraph,</hi> my Province is to <hi>corrupt the Manners of the Nation, and lay waſte their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199796:14"/>Morals, and my endeavours are more happily apply'd, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the little remainders of the Vertue of the Age.</hi> Now I am to perform all this, it ſeems, without making any thing <hi>veriſimilar</hi> or <hi>agreeable:</hi> Why, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> never ſet the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſuch a Task, to build <hi>Piramids</hi> without <hi>Brick</hi> or <hi>Straw.</hi> If the Fool knows it not, <hi>veriſimilitude</hi> and <hi>agreeableneſs,</hi> are the very Tools to do it; but I am willing to diſclaim them both, rather than to uſe them to ſo ill purpoſe as he has done.</p>
            <p>Yet even this their celebrated Writer, knows no more of <hi>Style</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> than the <hi>Northern Dedicator.</hi> As if <hi>Dulneſs</hi> and <hi>Clumſineſs</hi> were fatal to the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>TOM.</hi> 'Tis true, he is a <hi>Fool</hi> in <hi>three Languages</hi> more than the <hi>Poet,</hi> for they ſay, he underſtands <hi>Latine, Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> from all which, to my certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I acquit the other. <hi>Og</hi> may write againſt the King if he pleaſes, ſo long as he <hi>Drinks</hi> for him; and his <hi>Writings</hi> will never do the Government ſo much <hi>harm,</hi> as his <hi>Drinking</hi> does it <hi>good:</hi> for true Subjects, will not be much perverted by his <hi>Libels;</hi> but the Wine <hi>Duties</hi> riſe conſiderably by his <hi>Claret.</hi> He has often call'd me an <hi>Atheist</hi> in Print, I would believe more charitably of him; and that he only goes the <hi>broad way,</hi> becauſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is too <hi>narrow</hi> for him. He may ſee by this, I do not delight to meddle with his courſe of <hi>Life,</hi> and his <hi>Immoralities,</hi> though I have a long <hi>Bead-roll</hi> of them. I have hitherto contented my ſelf with the <hi>Ridiculous</hi> part of him, which is enough in all conſcience to employ one man: even without the ſtory of his late fall at the <hi>Old Devil,</hi> where he <hi>broke no Ribbs,</hi> becauſe the hardneſs of the <hi>Stairs</hi> cou'd reach <hi>no Bones;</hi> and for my part, I do not wonder how he came to <hi>fall,</hi> for I have always known him heavy; the Miracle is, how he got <hi>up again.</hi> I have heard of a <hi>Sea-Captain</hi> as <hi>fat</hi> as he, who to ſcape Arreſts, would lay himſelf flat upon the ground, and let the <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199796:15"/>carry him to <hi>Priſon,</hi> if they cou'd. If a Meſſenger or two, nay, we may put in three or four, ſhould come, he has friendly Advertiſement how to ſcape them. But to leave him, who is not worth any further conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, now I have done laughing at him, Wou'd every man knew his own Tallent, and that they who are only born for <hi>drinking,</hi> wou'd let both <hi>Poetry</hi> and <hi>Proſe</hi> alone.</p>
            <p>I am weary with traceing the Abſurdities and Miſtakes of our great Lawyer, ſome of which indeed are <hi>wilful;</hi> as where he calls the <hi>Trimmers,</hi> the <hi>more moderate ſort of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> It ſeems thoſe Polliticians are odious to both ſides; for neither own them to be theirs. We know them, and ſo does he too in his Conſcience, to be <hi>ſecret Whigs,</hi> if they are any thing. But now the deſigns of <hi>Whiggiſm</hi> are openly diſcover'd, they tack about to ſave a Stake, that is, they will not be villains to their own ruine. While the Government was to be deſtroyed, and there was probability of compaſſing it, no men were ſo violent as they; but ſince their <hi>Fortunes</hi> are in hazard by the <hi>Law,</hi> and their <hi>Places at Court</hi> by the <hi>Kings diſpleaſure,</hi> they pull in their horns, and talk more peaceably; in order, I ſuppoſe, to their vehemence on the right ſide, if they were to be believ'd. For in laying of Colours, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a <hi>Medium;</hi> Black and white are too far diſtant, to be plac'd directly by one another, without ſome ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to ſoften their contrarieties. 'Tis <hi>Mariana</hi> I think (but am not certain) that makes the following relation; and let the noble Family of <hi>Trimmers,</hi> read their own Fortune in it. <hi>Don Pedro, King of</hi> Caſtile, <hi>Sirnam'd</hi> the Cruel, <hi>who had been reſtor'd by the Valour of our</hi> Edward the Black Prince, <hi>was finally diſpoſſeſſ'd by</hi> Don Henry the Baſtard, <hi>and he enjoyed the Kingdom quietly, till his Death; which, when he felt approaching, he call'd his Son to him, and gave him this his laſt Counſel. I have,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>gain'd this Kingdon, which I leave you, by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199796:15"/>the Sword; for the Right of Inheritance was in</hi> Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro; <hi>but the favour of the People, who hated my Brother for his Tyranny, was to me inſtead of Title. You are now to be the Peaceable Poſſeſſor of of what I have unjuſtly gotten: and your Subjects are compos'd of theſe three ſorts of men. One Party eſpous'd my Brothers Quarrel, which was the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Lawful Cauſe; thoſe, though they were my Enemies, were men of Principle and Honour: cheriſh them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt them into Places of trust about you, for in them you may confide ſafely, who priz'd their</hi> Fidelity <hi>above their</hi> Fortune. <hi>Another ſort, are they who fought my Cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Don Pedro, <hi>to thoſe you are indeed oblig'd, becauſe of the accidental good they did me, for they intended only their</hi> private Benefit, <hi>and help'd to raiſe me, that I might afterwards promote them: You may continue them in their Offices, if you pleaſe; but truſt them no farther than you are forc'd, for what they did, was againſt their Conſcience. But there is a third ſort, which during the whole Wars, were Neuters; let them be cruſht on all occaſions, for</hi> their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs <hi>was only</hi> their own Security. <hi>They had neither Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage enough to ingage on my Side, nor Conſcience enough to help their Lawful Soveraign: <hi>therefore let them be made Examples, as the worſt ſort of intereſſed men, which certainly are Enemies to both, and would be profitable to neither.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have only a dark remembrance of this Story, and have not the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Author by me, but I think, I am not much miſtaken in the main of it: and whether true or falſe, the Counſel given, I am ſure, is ſuch, as ought in common prudence, to be practis'd againſt <hi>Trimmers,</hi> whether the <hi>Lawful</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> Cauſe <hi>prevail. Loyal</hi> men may juſtly be diſpleaſ'd with this <hi>Party,</hi> not for their <hi>Moderation,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> inſinuates; but becauſe, under that Maſque of <hi>ſeeming mildneſs,</hi> there lies hidden either a deep <hi>treachery,</hi> or at beſt, an <hi>interreſſed luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:199796:16"/>But he runs riot into almoſt treaſonable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as if <hi>Trimmers were hated becauſe they are not perfectly wicked, or perfectly deceiv'd, of the</hi> Catiline make, <hi>bold, and without underſtanding, that can adhaere to men that publickly profeſs Murthers, and applaud the deſign:</hi> By all which villanous names, he opprobriouſly calls His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt <hi>loyal Subjects;</hi> as if Men muſt be <hi>perfectly wicked</hi> who endeavour to ſupport a <hi>lawful Government;</hi> or <hi>perfectly deceiv'd,</hi> who on no occaſion dare take up arms againſt their <hi>Soveraign:</hi> as if <hi>acknowledging</hi> the <hi>right</hi> of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and <hi>reſolving</hi> to <hi>maintain</hi> it in the <hi>Line,</hi> were to be in a <hi>Catiline Conſpiracy;</hi> and at laſt, (which is ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous enough, after ſo much ſerious Treaſon) as if to <hi>clap the Duke of Guiſe,</hi> were to <hi>adhaere to men that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſs Murthers, and applaud the deſign of the Aſſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinating Poets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But together with his <hi>Villanies,</hi> pray let his <hi>incohaerences</hi> be obſerv'd. He commends the <hi>Trimmers</hi> (at leaſt tacitly excuſes them) for men of ſome <hi>moderation;</hi> and this in oppoſition to the inſtruments of wickedneſs of the <hi>Catiline</hi>-make, that are <hi>reſolute</hi> and <hi>forward,</hi> and <hi>without conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But he forgets all this in the next twenty lines; for there he gives them their own, and tells them roundly, <hi>in internecino bello medii pro hoſtibus habentur.</hi> Neutral men are Traytors, and aſſiſt by their indifferency to the deſtruction of the Government. The plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> of his <hi>meaning,</hi> is this; while matters are only in <hi>diſpute,</hi> and in <hi>machination,</hi> he is contented they ſhou'd be <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate;</hi> but when once the Faction can bring about a <hi>Civil War,</hi> then they are <hi>Traytors,</hi> if they declare not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it is not,</hi> he ſays, <hi>the Duke of</hi> Guiſe, <hi>who is to be aſſaſſinated, a turbulent wicked and haughty Courtier, but an innocent and gentle Prince:</hi> By his favour, <hi>our Duke of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199796:16"/>Guiſe,</hi> was neither <hi>Innocent</hi> nor <hi>Gentle,</hi> nor a Prince of the <hi>Blood Royal,</hi> though he pretended to deſcend from <hi>Charlemaign,</hi> and a <hi>Genealogy</hi> was printed to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for which the Author was puniſh'd, as he deſerv'd; witneſs <hi>Davila,</hi> and the <hi>Journals</hi> of <hi>Henry the Third,</hi> where the Story is at large related. Well, who is it then? why, 'tis a <hi>Prince who has no fault, but that he is the Kings Son:</hi> Then he has no fault by conſequence; for I am certain, that's no fault of his. The reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, is ſo ſilly, and ſo fulſome, as if he meant it all <hi>in ridicule.</hi> And to conclude the Jeaſt, he ſays, that <hi>the best People of</hi> England, <hi>have no other way left, to ſhow their Loyalty to the King, their Religion and Government, in long intervals of Parliament, than by proſecuting his Son, for the ſake of the King, and his own merit, with all the Demonſtrations of the higheſt eſteem.</hi> Yes, I can tell them one other way to expreſs their Loyalty, which is, to <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and to <hi>reſpect</hi> his <hi>Brother,</hi> as the <hi>next Lawful Succeſſor;</hi> their <hi>Religion commands</hi> them both, and the <hi>Government</hi> is ſecur'd in ſo doing. But why <hi>in Intervals of Parliament?</hi> How are the more oblig'd to honour the <hi>Kings Son</hi> out of Parliament, than in it? And why this proſecution of Love for the <hi>Kings Sake?</hi> Has he order'd more Love to be ſhown to one Son, than to another? Indeed, his own quality, is cauſe ſufficient for all men to reſpect him, and I am of their number, who truly honour him, and who wiſh him better than this <hi>miſerable Sycophant;</hi> for I wiſh him, from his Fathers Royal <hi>Kindneſs</hi> what <hi>Juſtice</hi> can make him, which is a greater Honour, than the Rabble can confer upon him.</p>
            <p>But our Author finds, that <hi>Commendation</hi> is no more <hi>his Talent,</hi> than <hi>Flattery</hi> was that of <hi>Eſop</hi>'s <hi>Aſs;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore falls immediately, from <hi>pawing</hi> with his <hi>fore-feet,</hi> and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199796:17"/>
               <hi>grinning</hi> upon <hi>one Prince,</hi> to downright <hi>braying</hi> againſt <hi>another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſays I have not uſ'd <hi>my Patron Duke much better: for I have put him under a moſt diſmal and unfortunate Character, of a Succeſſor, excluded from the Crown by Act of State, for his Religion; who fought his way to the Crown, chang'd his Religion, and died by the hand of a Roman Aſſaſſinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it pleaſe his <hi>Royal Highneſs</hi> to be <hi>my Patron,</hi> I have reaſon to be proud of it; becauſe he never yet forſook any man, whom he has had the goodneſs to own for his. But how have I put him under <hi>an unfortunate Character?</hi> the <hi>Authors</hi> of the <hi>Reflections,</hi> and our <hi>John a Nokes,</hi> have not layd their noddles together about this Accuſation. For 'tis their buſineſs to prove the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> to have been a moſt <hi>ſucceſsful, magnanimous, gentle,</hi> and <hi>grateful Prince:</hi> in which Character they have follow'd the ſtream of all <hi>Hiſtorians.</hi> How then happens this jarring amongſt friends, that the ſame man is put under ſuch <hi>diſmal cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> on <hi>one</hi> ſide, and ſo <hi>fortunate</hi> on the <hi>other,</hi> by the Writers of the <hi>ſame Party?</hi> The anſwer is very plain, that they take the cauſe by ſeveral handles. <hi>They</hi> who will not have the <hi>Duke</hi> reſemble the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> have <hi>magnify</hi>'d the Character of <hi>that</hi> Prince, to <hi>debaſe</hi> his <hi>Royal Highneſs;</hi> and therein done what they can to ſhow the <hi>diſparity.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> who will have it to be the <hi>Dukes Character,</hi> has <hi>blacken'd that King</hi> as much as he is able, to ſhow the likeneſs. Now this wou'd be ridiculous plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a <hi>Barr,</hi> by Lawyers retain'd for the ſame Cauſe; and both ſides wou'd call each other fools, becauſe the <hi>Jury</hi> betwixt them wou'd be <hi>confounded,</hi> and perhaps the <hi>Judges</hi> too.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199796:17"/>
            <p>But this it is to have a bad Cauſe, which puts men of neceſſity upon knavery; and that knavery is commonly found out. Well Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> has in another place confeſſ'd himſelf to be in <hi>paſſion,</hi> and that's the reaſon he is ſo groſly miſtaken in opening of the Cauſe. For firſt the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> was neither under <hi>diſmall,</hi> nor <hi>unfortunate cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances.</hi> Before the end of that very Sentence, our Lawyer has confeſſ'd that <hi>he fought his way to the Crown;</hi> that is, he gloriouſly vanquiſh'd all his Rebells, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily poſſeſt his Inheritance many years after he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain'd it. In the next place, he was <hi>never excluded from the Crown by Act of State.</hi> He chang'd his <hi>Religion</hi> indeed, but not till he had almoſt <hi>weather'd</hi> the <hi>Storm,</hi> recover'd the beſt part of his <hi>Estate,</hi> and gain'd ſome glorious <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories</hi> in <hi>pitch'd Battels;</hi> ſo that his <hi>changing</hi> cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injuſtice be attributed to his <hi>fear. Monſieur Chiverny,</hi> in his <hi>Memoirs</hi> of thoſe times plainly tells us, that <hi>he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly promiſed to his Predeceſſour</hi> Henry the Third, <hi>then dying, that he wou'd become a</hi> Romaniſt; and <hi>Davila,</hi> though he ſays not this <hi>directly,</hi> yet <hi>denyes</hi> it not. By whoſe hands <hi>Henry the fourth</hi> died, is notoriouſly known; but it is indiviouſly urg'd, both by Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flectors:</hi> for we may, to our ſhame, remember, that a King of our own Country was <hi>barbarouſly murther'd</hi> by his <hi>Subjects,</hi> who profeſſ'd the <hi>ſame Religion;</hi> though I believe that neither <hi>Jaques Clement,</hi> nor <hi>Ravillac,</hi> were <hi>better Papiſts,</hi> than the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were <hi>Protestants:</hi> So that their <hi>Argument</hi> only proves that there are <hi>Rogues</hi> of all <hi>Religions: Iliacos intra mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros peccatur &amp; extra.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> follows his blow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that I have <hi>offer'd a Juſtification of an Act of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion againſt a Popiſh Succeſſour in a Proteſtant Kingdom, by remembring what was done against the King of</hi> Navarre, <hi>who was</hi> de facto <hi>excluded by an Act of State.</hi> My Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, I perceive, is very willing to call that an Act of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199796:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199796:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199796:19"/>
               <hi>Excluſion,</hi> and an Act of <hi>State,</hi> which is only in our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, call'd a <hi>Bill:</hi> for <hi>Henry the third</hi> cou'd never be gain'd to <hi>paſs</hi> it, though it was propoſ'd by the <hi>three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> at <hi>Blois.</hi> The <hi>Reflectors</hi> are more modeſt; for they profeſs, (though I am afraid it is ſomewhat againſt the grain) that a <hi>Vote</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> is not an <hi>Act:</hi> But the times are turn'd upon them, and they dare ſpeak no other Language. Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> indeed is a <hi>bold Republican,</hi> and tells you the bottom of their meaning. Yet why ſhould it make the <hi>courage of his Royal Highneſs quail, to find himſelf under this repreſentation?</hi> which by our Authors favour, is neither <hi>diſmal,</hi> nor <hi>diſastrous. Henry the Fourth</hi> eſcap'd this dreadful Machine of the <hi>League:</hi> I ſay <hi>dreadful;</hi> for the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> were at that time compoſ'd generally of <hi>Guiſards, factious, hot headed rebellious interreſſed men:</hi> The King in <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> was but his <hi>Brother-in-Law;</hi> and at that time publickly his <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> for the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> was then in <hi>arms</hi> againſt him: and yet the ſenſe of <hi>Common Juſtice,</hi> and the good of his <hi>People</hi> ſo prevail'd, that he withſtood the Project of the <hi>States,</hi> which he alſo knew was levell'd at <hi>himſelf;</hi> for had the Excluſion proceeded, he had been immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately lay'd by, and the Lieutenancy of <hi>France</hi> conferr'd on <hi>Guiſe:</hi> after which the Rebel wou'd certainly have put up his Title for the Crown. In the Caſe of his <hi>Royal Highneſs,</hi> only <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>three Estates</hi> have offer'd at the <hi>Excluſion;</hi> and have been conſtantly oppoſ'd by the <hi>other two,</hi> and by his <hi>Majeſty:</hi> Neither is it any way probable, that the like will ever be again attempted: For the <hi>fatal Conſequences,</hi> as well as the <hi>Illegality</hi> of that Deſign, are ſeen through already by the People. So that inſtead of offering a <hi>juſtification</hi> of an Act of <hi>Excluſion,</hi> I have expoſ'd a <hi>rebellious, impious,</hi> and <hi>fruitleſs</hi> contrivance <hi>tending</hi> to it. If we look on the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> when they were in their right wits,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199796:19"/>before they were <hi>intoxicated</hi> by the <hi>League,</hi> (at leaſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) we ſhall find them <hi>addreſſing</hi> to King <hi>Henry the third</hi> in another Key, concerning the King of <hi>Navarr's Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> though he was at that time (as they call'd it) a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſ'd Heretique.</hi> And to this purpoſe I will quote a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage out of the <hi>Journals</hi> of <hi>Henry the Third,</hi> ſo much magnify'd by my Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>Towards the end of <hi>September,</hi> 1585. there was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed at <hi>Paris,</hi> a Bull of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> againſt the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Conde:</hi> The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris,</hi> made their <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> to the King up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, which was both grave, and worthy of the Place they held, and of the Authority they have in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Saying, for concluſion, that <hi>their Court had found the Style of this Bull, ſo full of Innovation, and ſo diſtant from the Modeſty of</hi> antient Popes, <hi>that they cou'd not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand in it, the voice of an</hi> Apoſtles Succeſſor; <hi>foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as they found not in their Records, nor in the ſearch of all Antiquity, that the Princes of</hi> France, <hi>had ever been ſubject to the Juſtice or Juriſdiction of the</hi> Pope, <hi>and they cou'd not take it into conſideration, till firſt he made appear the Right which he pretended in the Tranſlation of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, eſtabliſh'd and ordain'd by Almighty God, before the Name of Pope was heard of in the World.</hi> 'Tis plain by this, that the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> acknowledg'd an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Right of Succeſſion in the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> though of a contrary Religion to their own: And though after the Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> Murther at <hi>Blois,</hi> the City of <hi>Paris</hi> revolted from their Obedience to their <hi>King,</hi> pretending that he was fallen from the Crown, by reaſon of that and other Actions, with which they charg'd him; yet the ſum of all their Power to renounce him, and create the Duke of <hi>Mayenne Lieutenant General,</hi> depended <hi>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately</hi> on the <hi>Popes authority;</hi> which as you ſee, but three years before, they had peremptorily denied.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:199796:20"/>
            <p>The Colledg of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> began the Dance, by their Determination, that the <hi>Kingly Right was forfeited;</hi> and ſtripping him of all his <hi>Dignities,</hi> they call'd him plain <hi>Henry de Valois:</hi> after this, ſays my Author, <hi>ſixteen Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals</hi> (by which he means the <hi>Council,</hi> of that <hi>Number</hi>) <hi>having adminiſtred the Oath of Government to the Duke of</hi> Mayenne, <hi>to take in quality of</hi> Lievtenant General <hi>of the Eſtate and Crown of</hi> France; <hi>the ſame ridiculous Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, was confirm'd to him, by an</hi> imaginary Parliament, <hi>the</hi> true Parliament <hi>being detain'd Priſoners, in divers of the City-Gaols, and two new Seals were order'd to be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately made, with this Inſcription:</hi> The Seal of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>France.</hi> I need not inlarge on this Relation, 'tis evident from hence, that the <hi>Sorboniſts</hi> were the <hi>Original,</hi> and our <hi>Schiſmatiques</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> were the <hi>Copiers</hi> of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> that <hi>Paris</hi> began, and <hi>London</hi> follow'd.</p>
            <p>The next Lines of my Author are, that <hi>a Gentleman of Paris, made the Duke of</hi> Mayenne<hi>'s Picture to be drawn, with a Crown Imperial on his Head,</hi> and I have heard of an <hi>Engliſh Nobleman,</hi> who has at this day, the Picture of <hi>Old Oliver,</hi> with this <hi>Motto</hi> underneath it, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam vixeris.</hi> All this while, this cannot be reckon'd an Act of <hi>State,</hi> for the <hi>Depoſing King Henry the Third;</hi> becauſe it was an Act of <hi>Ouvert Rebellion</hi> in the <hi>Pariſians:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could the holding of the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, by the ſame Duke of <hi>Mayenne,</hi> devolve any Right on him, in prejudice of King <hi>Henry the Fourth;</hi> though thoſe pretended States, declar'd his Title void, on the account of his <hi>Religion:</hi> becauſe thoſe Eſtates could neither be call'd nor holden, but by and under the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Lawful King.</hi> It wou'd take more time than I have allow'd, for this Vindication, or I cou'd
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199796:20"/>eaſily trace from the <hi>French History,</hi> what Misfortunes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>France,</hi> and how near it was to Ruine, by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors to alter the Succeſſion. For firſt, it was actually <hi>Diſmembred,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Merceur</hi> ſetting up a Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Dutchy of <hi>Bretagne, Independant</hi> of the <hi>Crown:</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> had an evident deſign to be elected <hi>King,</hi> by the favour of the <hi>People</hi> and the <hi>Pope:</hi> the young Dukes of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and of <hi>Nemours,</hi> aſpir'd with the intereſt of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to be choſen, by their Marriage with the <hi>Infanta Izabella.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> was for cantling out ſome part of <hi>France,</hi> which lay next his Territories; and the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> had before the Death of <hi>Henry the Third,</hi> actually poſſeſs'd himſelf of the <hi>Marquiſate</hi> of <hi>Saluces.</hi> But above all, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented theſe Civil Wars, in hopes to reduce that flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kingdom, under their own <hi>Monarchy.</hi> To as many, and as great Miſchiefs, ſhould we be evidently ſubject; if we ſhould madly ingage our ſelves, in the like Practiſes of altering the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> which our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King, in his Royal Wiſdom well forſaw; and has cut up that accurſed Project by the Roots; which will render the memory of his <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Prudence, Immortal</hi> and <hi>Sacred to future Ages,</hi> for having not only preſerv'd our preſent quiet, but ſecur'd the Peace of our Poſterity.</p>
            <p>'Tis clearly manifeſt, that no Act of <hi>State</hi> paſs'd, to the <hi>Excluſion</hi> of either, the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> or of <hi>Henry the Fourth;</hi> conſider him, in either of the two circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: but <hi>Oracle Hunt,</hi> taking this for granted, wou'd prove <hi>à fortiori,</hi> that <hi>if a Proteſtant Prince, were actually excluded from a Popiſh Kingdom, then a Popiſh Succeſſor is more reaſonably to be excluded from a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Kingdom; becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>a Proteſtant Prince, is under no Obligation to deſtroy his Popiſh Subjects, but a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prince, is to deſtroy his Proteſtant Subjects:</hi> upon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199796:21"/>which bare ſuppoſition, without farther Proof, he calls him <hi>inſufferable Tyrant,</hi> and the worſt of <hi>Monſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I take the matter quite otherwiſe, and bind my ſelf to maintain, that there is not, nor can be any Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, for a King to deſtroy his Subjects of a contrary Perſwaſion, to the eſtabliſh'd Religion of his Country: for <hi>quatenus Subjects,</hi> of what Religion ſoever, <hi>he is infallibly bound</hi> to preſerve and cheriſh, and not to deſtroy them: and this is the firſt duty of a Lawful Soveraign, as ſuch, antecedent to any tye or conſideration of his Religion. Indeed, in thoſe Countries where the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> is intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, it goes harder with <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the reaſon is manifeſt, becauſe the Proteſtant Religion has not gotten footing there, and ſeverity is the means to keep it out: But to make this inſtance, reach <hi>England,</hi> our Religion muſt not only be chang'd (which in it ſelf, is almoſt impoſſible to imagine) but the Council of <hi>Trent receiv'd</hi> and the <hi>Inquiſition admitted,</hi> which <hi>many Popiſh Countries</hi> have rejected. I forget not the Cruelties, which were exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſ'd in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, againſt the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I any way excuſe them: But it follows not, that every <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi> ſhou'd take example by them, for every ones Conſcience of the ſame Religion, is not guided by the ſame Dictates in his Government: Neither does it follow, that if one be cruel, another muſt; eſpecially, when there is a ſtronger Obligation, and greater Intereſt to the contrary: For if a <hi>Popiſh King</hi> in <hi>England</hi> ſhou'd be bound to deſtroy his <hi>Proteſtant People,</hi> I wou'd ask the Queſtion, over whom he meant to Reign afterwards? and how many Subjects would be left?</p>
            <p>In Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, the Proteſtant Religion had ſcarcely taken root: And it is reaſonable to be ſuppos'd, that ſhe found the number of Papiſts, equalling that of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199796:21"/>the Proteſtants, at her entrance to the Kingdom; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if we reckon into the account thoſe who were the <hi>Trimmers</hi> of the times; I mean ſuch, who privately were Papiſts, though under her Proteſtant Predeceſſour they appear'd otherwiſe. Therefore her difficulties in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting her reform'd Subjects, were far from being ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperable, as ours now are, when the ſtrength and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Papiſts is ſo very inconſiderable. They who caſt in the Church of <hi>England</hi> as ready to embrace <hi>Popery,</hi> are either <hi>Knaves</hi> enough to know they <hi>lye,</hi> or <hi>Fools</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough not to have conſider'd the <hi>Tenents</hi> of that Church, which are <hi>diametrically oppoſite</hi> to <hi>Popery;</hi> and more ſo than any of the <hi>Sects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to inſiſt on the quiet and ſecurity, which Proteſtant Subjects at this day enjoy in ſome parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> under Popiſh Princes; where I have been aſſur'd, that <hi>Maſs</hi> is ſaid, and a <hi>Lutheran Sermon</hi> preach'd in different parts of the fame Church, on the ſame day, without diſturbance on either ſide; nor on the Priviledges granted by <hi>Henry the Fourth</hi> of <hi>France</hi> to his Party, after he had forſaken their Opinions, which they quietly poſſeſſ'd for a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death:</p>
            <p>The <hi>French Hiſtories</hi> are full of <hi>Examples,</hi> manifeſtly proving, that the fierceſt of their <hi>Popiſh Princes</hi> have not thought themſelves bound to deſtroy their <hi>Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects:</hi> and the ſeveral <hi>Edicts</hi> granted under them, in favor of the <hi>Reform'd Religion,</hi> are pregnant inſtances of this truth. I am not much given to Quotations, but <hi>Davila</hi> lies open for every man to read. <hi>Tolerations,</hi> and <hi>free exerciſe of Religion,</hi> granted more <hi>amply</hi> in <hi>ſome,</hi> more <hi>reſtraindly</hi> in <hi>others,</hi> are no ſign that thoſe Princes held themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to deſtroy men of a different Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It will be ſaid thoſe Tolerations were gain'd by force
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199796:22"/>of <hi>Arms:</hi> In the firſt place 'tis no great credit to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, that the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Rebels.</hi> But the truth is, they were only <hi>Geneva Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> and their opinions were far diſtant from thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which teaches <hi>paſſive obedience</hi> to all her Sons, and not to propagate <hi>Religion</hi> by <hi>Rebellion.</hi> But 'tis further to be conſider'd, that thoſe <hi>French</hi> Kings, though Papiſts, thought the preſervation of their Subjects, and the publick Peace, were to be conſider'd, before the gratification of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and though the number of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> exceeded that of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> in the proportion of three to one; though the Proteſtants were always beaten when they fought, and though the Popes preſs'd continually with Exhortations and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to extirpate <hi>Calviniſm,</hi> yet Kings thought it enough to continue in their own Religion themſelves, without for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it upon their Subjects, much leſs deſtroying them who profeſſ'd another. But it will be objected thoſe Edicts of Toleration were not kept on the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſide: They wou'd anſwer, becauſe the Proteſtants ſtretch'd their Privileges further than was granted: and that they often relapſ'd into <hi>Rebellion:</hi> But whether or no the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were in <hi>fault,</hi> I leave Hiſtory to determine: 'tis matter of <hi>fact,</hi> that they were barbarouſly <hi>maſſacred,</hi> under the protection of the <hi>Publick Faith:</hi> Therefore to argue fairly, either an <hi>Oath</hi> from <hi>Protestants</hi> is not to be <hi>taken</hi> by a <hi>Popiſh Prince;</hi> or if <hi>taken,</hi> ought inviolably to be <hi>preſerv'd.</hi> For when we oblige our ſelves to any one, 'tis not his perſon we ſo much conſider, as that of the moſt high God, who is call'd to witneſs this our action: and 'tis to him we are to diſcharge our Conſcience. Neither is there, or can be any <hi>tye</hi> on <hi>humane Society,</hi> when that of an <hi>Oath</hi> is no more regarded: which being an appeal to God, he is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Judge of it; and Chronicles are not ſilent how often he has puniſh'd perjur'd Kings. The inſtance of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199796:22"/>
               <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> breaking his faith with <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rath the Turk,</hi> at the inſtigation of <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Popes Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> and his miſerable death enſuing it, ſhows that even to <hi>Infidels,</hi> much more to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that obligation ought to be accounted ſacred. And I the rather urge this, becauſe it is an Argument taken almoſt <hi>verbatim</hi> from a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> who accuſes <hi>Catharine de Medicis</hi> for violating her word given to the <hi>Protestants</hi> during her <hi>Regency</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> What ſecurities in particular we have, that our own Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liberties wou'd be preſerv'd, though under a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Succeſſour,</hi> any one may inform himſelf at large in a Book lately written by the Reverend and learned Doctor <hi>Hicks,</hi> call'd <hi>Jovian,</hi> in anſwer to <hi>Julian the Apoſtate:</hi> in which, that truly Chriſtian Author has ſatisfy'd all ſcruples which reaſonable men can make, and prov'd that we are in no danger of loſing either; and wherein alſo, if thoſe aſſurances ſhou'd all fail (which is almoſt morally impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) the Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> is <hi>unanſwerably demonſtrated:</hi> a Doctrine deliver'd with ſo much ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and reſignation of ſpirit, that it ſeems evident the Aſſertor of it is ready, if there were occaſion, to ſeal it with his blood.</p>
            <p>I have done with mannerly Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> who is only <hi>magni nominis umbra;</hi> the moſt <hi>malicious,</hi> and withal, the moſt <hi>incohaerent ignorant Scribler</hi> of the whole Party. I inſult not over his misfortunes, though he has himſelf occaſion'd them: and though I will not take his own excuſe, that he is in paſſion, I will make a better for him; for I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him crack'd: and if he ſhould return to <hi>England,</hi> am charitable enough to wiſh his only Priſon might be <hi>Bedlam.</hi> This Apology is truer than that he makes for me: for <hi>writing a Play,</hi> as I conceive, is not entring into the <hi>Obſervators Province;</hi> neither is it the <hi>Obſervators</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>to confound truth with falſehood, to put out the eyes of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199796:23"/>People, and leave them without underſtanding.</hi> The quarrel of the Party to him, is that he has <hi>undeceiv'd</hi> the <hi>ignorant,</hi> and laid open the ſhameful contrivances of the <hi>new vampt Aſſociation:</hi> that though he is <hi>on the wrong ſide of life,</hi> as he calls it, yet he pleads not his <hi>Age</hi> to be <hi>Emeritus:</hi> that in ſhort, he has left the Faction as bare of <hi>Arguments,</hi> as <hi>Eſops Bird</hi> of <hi>feathers;</hi> and plum'd them of all thoſe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies and evaſions which they borrowed from <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for my <hi>Templar</hi> and <hi>Poet</hi> in <hi>aſſociation</hi> for a <hi>Libel,</hi> like the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in a <hi>fiery Sign:</hi> what the <hi>one</hi> wants in <hi>Wit,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> muſt ſupply in <hi>Law.</hi> As for Malice, their quota's are indifferently well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted: the <hi>rough Draught</hi> I take for granted, is the <hi>Poets,</hi> the <hi>finiſhings</hi> the <hi>Lawyers.</hi> They begin, that in order to one Mr. <hi>Friend's</hi> commands, one of them went to ſee the Play. This was not the <hi>Poet,</hi> I am certain, for no body ſaw him there, and he is not of a <hi>Size</hi> to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd.</hi> But the <hi>Mountain,</hi> they ſay, <hi>was deliver'd of a Mouſe:</hi> I have been <hi>Goſſip</hi> to many ſuch <hi>Labors</hi> of a <hi>dull fat Scribler,</hi> where the <hi>Mountain</hi> has been <hi>bigger,</hi> and the <hi>Mouſe leſs.</hi> The next Sally, is on the <hi>City Elections,</hi> and a Charge is brought againſt my <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> and the two <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> for excluding true <hi>Electors.</hi> I have heard, that a <hi>Whig Gentleman</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> hired a <hi>Livery-Gown,</hi> to give his Voice among the <hi>Companies</hi> at <hi>Guild-Hall:</hi> let the queſtion be put, <hi>whether or no, he were a true Elector?</hi> Then their own <hi>Juries</hi> are commended from ſeveral <hi>Topiques;</hi> they are the <hi>Wiſeſt, Richeſt,</hi> and moſt <hi>Conſcientious:</hi> to which is anſwer'd <hi>Ignoramus.</hi> But our <hi>Juries</hi> give moſt <hi>prodigious</hi> and <hi>unheard of Damages.</hi> Hithero there is nothing but <hi>Boys-play</hi> in our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: <hi>My Mill grinds Pepper and Spice, your Mill grinds Rats and Mice.</hi> They go on, <hi>if I may be allow'd to</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199796:23"/>judge (as men that do not <hi>Poetize,</hi> may be Judges of Wit, <hi>Humane nature</hi> and <hi>Common Decencies:</hi>) So then the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is begun with <hi>I:</hi> there is but one of them puts in for a Judges Place: <hi>that's he in the Gray:</hi> but preſently 'tis men; <hi>two more in Buckram,</hi> wou'd be <hi>Judges</hi> too. <hi>Neither</hi> of them it ſeems, <hi>Poetize;</hi> that's true, but both of them are in at <hi>Rhime Doggrel;</hi> witneſs the Song a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Tunbridge-Ballad.</hi> By the way, I find all my Scribling Enemies have a mind to be <hi>Judges,</hi> and <hi>Chief Barons:</hi> proceed Gentlemen. <hi>This Play (as I am inform'd by ſome, who have a nearer Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with the Poets and the Players, than I have.)</hi> Which of the two <hi>Soſia's</hi> is it that now ſpeaks? If the <hi>Lawyer,</hi> 'tis true, he has but little <hi>Communication</hi> with the <hi>Players:</hi> if the <hi>Poet,</hi> the <hi>Players</hi> have but <hi>little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> with <hi>him.</hi> For 'tis not long ago, he ſaid to ſome body, <hi>By G— my Lord, thoſe</hi> Tory-rogues <hi>will act. none of my Plays.</hi> Well, but the Accuſation, that this Play was once written by <hi>another,</hi> and then 'twas call'd the <hi>Pariſian Maſſacre:</hi> Such a Play, I have heard indeed was written; but I never ſaw it. Whether this be any of it or no, I can ſay no more, than for my own part of it. But pray, who denies the unparalleld villany of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in that bloody <hi>Maſſacre?</hi> I have enquired, why it was not Acted, and heard it was ſtopt, by the interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an <hi>Ambaſſador,</hi> who was willing to ſave the Credit of his Country, and not to have the Memory of an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo barbarous, reviv'd. But that I tempted my Friend to alter it, is a notorious <hi>Whiggiſm</hi> to ſave the <hi>broader Word.</hi> The <hi>Sicilian Veſpers</hi> I have had <hi>Plotted</hi> by me above theſe ſeven <hi>years:</hi> The Story of it, I found under borow'd Names in <hi>Giraldo Cinthio;</hi> but the Rape in my Tragedy of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> was ſo like it, that I forbore the Writing. But what had this to do with <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> for the <hi>Maſſacres</hi> and the <hi>Maſſacred</hi> were all Papiſts.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199796:24"/>
            <p>But 'tis obſervable, they ſay, that though the <hi>Maſſacre cou'd not be acted, as it was firſt written againſt Papiſts, yet when it was turn'd upon Proteſtants, it found reception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all's come out, the Scandal of the Story, turns at laſt upon the <hi>Government:</hi> that <hi>Patroniſes Popiſh Plays,</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids Proteſtant.</hi> Ours is to be a <hi>Popiſh Play,</hi> why? becauſe it expoſes the Villany of <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Rebels?</hi> Prove them firſt to be <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and ſee what you will get by it when you have done? your Party are certainly the men whom the Play attaques; and ſo far I will help you: the Deſigns and Actions repreſented in the Play, are ſuch as you have Copyed from the <hi>League;</hi> for though you have wickedneſs enough, yet you wanted the <hi>Wit</hi> to make a <hi>new Contrivance.</hi> But for ſhame, while you are carrying on ſuch palpable villany, do not aſſume the name of <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> You will tell us, you are friends to the <hi>Government,</hi> and the Kings <hi>beſt Subjects;</hi> but all the while, you are aſperſing both <hi>it</hi> and <hi>him.</hi> Who ſhall be Judges, whether you are Friends or not? the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or <hi>you?</hi> Have not all Rebels always ſung the ſame Song? Was ever Thief or Murtherer Fool enough to plead <hi>Guilty?</hi> For your Love and Loyalty to the King, they who mean him beſt amongſt you, are no better Subjects than <hi>Duke Trinculo:</hi> They wou'd be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he ſhou'd be <hi>Viceroy,</hi> ſo they may be <hi>Viceroys</hi> over him.</p>
            <p>The next Accuſation is particular to me, <hi>that I the ſaid</hi> Bays, <hi>wou'd falſly and felloniouſly, have robb'd</hi> Nat. Lee, <hi>of his ſhare in the Reputation of</hi> Oedipus: Now I am <hi>Culprit;</hi> I writ the firſt and third Acts of <hi>Oedipus,</hi> and drew the <hi>Scenary</hi> of the <hi>whole Play:</hi> when ever I have own'd a farther Proportion, let my Accuſers ſpeak: this
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199796:24"/>was meant miſchievouſly, to ſet us two at variance: Who is the <hi>old Serpent</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi> now? When my Friends help my barren Fancy, I am thankful for it: I do not uſe to receive aſſiſtance, and afterwards ungratefully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own it.</p>
            <p>Not long after, <hi>Exemplary Puniſhment</hi> is due to me, for this moſt <hi>deviliſh Parallel.</hi> 'Tis a deviliſh one indeed; but who can help it, if I draw <hi>Devils</hi> like <hi>one another,</hi> the fault is in themſelves for being ſo: I neither made their Horns nor Claws, nor cloven Feet: I know not what I ſhou'd have done, unleſs I had drawn the <hi>Devil</hi> a <hi>handſom proper Gentleman,</hi> like the Painter in the Fable, to have made a <hi>Friend</hi> of him; but I ought to be <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarily puniſh</hi>'d <hi>for it;</hi> when the <hi>Devil</hi> gets <hi>uppermoſt,</hi> I ſhall <hi>expect</hi> it. <hi>In the mean time, let Magiſtrates (that reſpect their Oaths and Office)</hi> which words you ſee, are put into a <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> as (if God help us) we had none ſuch now; let them put the Law in execution, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>leud Scriblers,</hi> the <hi>Mark</hi> will be too <hi>fair</hi> upon a <hi>Pillory,</hi> for a <hi>Turnip</hi> or a <hi>rotten Egg</hi> to <hi>miſs</hi> it. But for my part, I have not Malice enough, to wiſh him ſo much harm; not ſo much as to have a Hair of his head periſh, much leſs, that one whole ſide of it ſhould be diſmantled: I am no Informer who writ ſuch a Song, or ſuch a <hi>Libel,</hi> if the <hi>Dulneſs</hi> betrays him not, he is <hi>ſafe</hi> for <hi>me.</hi> And may the ſame <hi>dulneſs</hi> preſerve him ever from <hi>publick Juſtice:</hi> 'tis a ſufficient thick <hi>Mad-wall,</hi> betwixt <hi>him</hi> and <hi>Law:</hi> 'tis his Guardian Angel, that protects him from Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, becauſe in ſpight of him, he cannot deſerve it. 'Tis that which preſerves him innocent, when he means moſt miſchief; and makes him a <hi>Saint,</hi> when he intends to be a <hi>Devil.</hi> He can never offend enough, to need the Mercy of the <hi>Government;</hi> for 'tis <hi>beholding</hi> to him, that he writes againſt it: and he never offers at a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199796:25"/>
               <hi>Satyr,</hi> but he converts his <hi>Readers</hi> to the <hi>contrary pinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of the ſucceeding Pargraphs, are intended for <hi>very Ciceronian:</hi> There the <hi>Lawyer</hi> flouriſhes in the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit,</hi> and the <hi>Poet</hi> ſtands in <hi>Socks</hi> amongſt the Crowd to hear him. Now for <hi>Narration, Refutation, Calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Aggravation,</hi> and the whole <hi>Artillery</hi> of <hi>Tropes</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> to defend the Proceedings at <hi>Guild-Hall:</hi> the moſt minute circumſtances of the Elections, are deſcrib'd ſo lively, that a man, who had not heard he was there in a <hi>Livery-Gown,</hi> might ſuſpect, there was a <hi>quorum pars magna fui</hi> in the Caſe: and multitudes of Electors, juſt as well qualified as himſelf, might give their Party the greater Number: but throw back their <hi>guilt Shillings,</hi> which were told for <hi>Guinnies,</hi> and their true Summ was conſiderably leſs. Well, there was no Rebellion at this time, therefore ſays my Adverſary, there was no <hi>Parallel.</hi> 'Tis true, there was no <hi>Rebellion;</hi> but whoever told him, that I intended this <hi>Parallel</hi> ſo far? if the likeneſs had been throughout, I may gueſs by their good will to me, that I had never liv'd to write it. But to ſhow his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, which I believe wilful, the Play was wholly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a month or two before the laſt Election of the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs.</hi> Yet, it ſeems there was ſome kind of <hi>Propheſie</hi> in the Caſe: and till the Faction gets clear of a <hi>Riot,</hi> a part of the Compariſon will hold even there; yet, if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to remember, there has been a King of <hi>England</hi> forc'd by the Inhabitants from his <hi>Imperial Town.</hi> 'Tis true, the Son has had better fortune than the Father; but the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that he has now a ſtronger Party in the <hi>City,</hi> than his Enemies: the <hi>Government</hi> of it is ſecur'd in <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> and <hi>Prudent Hands,</hi> and the Party is to weak to puſh their deſigns farther. <hi>They reſcued not their beloved Sheriffs, at a time</hi> (he tells you) <hi>when they had moſt important
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199796:25"/>uſe of them.</hi> What the importancy of the occaſion was, I will not ſearch; 'tis well if their own Conſciences will acquit them. But let them be never ſo much belov'd, their Adherents knew it was a Lawful Authority that ſent them to the <hi>Tower;</hi> and an Authority, which to their ſorrow, they were not able to <hi>reſiſt:</hi> ſo that if four men guarded them without diſturbance, and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of their ſtrength, at broad noon day, and at full Exchange time, it was no more their honeſty, to ſtand looking on with their hands in their Pockets, than it is of a ſmall Band of <hi>Robbers,</hi> to let a <hi>Caravan</hi> go by, which is too ſtrong for them to aſſault.</p>
            <p>After this, I am call'd after the old rate, <hi>looſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Scribler,</hi> and 'tis well I ſcape ſo cheap: bear your good fortune moderately, Mr. <hi>Poet:</hi> for as looſe and as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous as I am, if I had written for your Party, your Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wou'd have been cut off, as uſeleſs. But they muſt take up with <hi>Settle,</hi> and ſuch as they can get: <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew-Fair Writers,</hi> and <hi>Bartholomew-Cloſe Printers;</hi> there's a famine of Wit amongſt them, they are forc'd to give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable rates, and after all to have only Carrion for their money.</p>
            <p>Then I am <hi>an ignorant fellow for not knowing there were no Juries in Paris:</hi> I do not remember I have written any ſuch thing: but whoever did, I am confident it was not his <hi>ignorance.</hi> Perhaps he had a mind to bring the caſe a little nearer home: if they had not <hi>Juries</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> we had them from the <hi>Normans,</hi> who were <hi>French-men:</hi> and as you manag'd them, we had as good have had none in <hi>London:</hi> Let it ſatisfie you we have them now; and ſome of your looſe and infamous Scriblers may come to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it a little better.</p>
            <p>The next is the Juſtification of a Noble Peer deceaſ'd: the Caſe is known, and I have no quarrel to his memory:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199796:26"/>let it ſleep; he is now before another Judge. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after I am ſaid to have intended <hi>an abuſe to the Houſe of Commons;</hi> which is call'd by our Authors, <hi>the moſt Auguſt Aſſembly of Europe.</hi> They are to prove I have abuſ'd that Houſe; but 'tis manifeſt They have leſſen'd the Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> by owning the Commons to be the <hi>more August Aſſembly.</hi> 'Tis an Houſe choſen (they ſay) by every <hi>Proteſtant</hi> who has a conſiderable Inheritance in <hi>England;</hi> which word <hi>conſiderable</hi> ſignifies forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <hi>per annum</hi> of free Land. For the intereſt of the loyal Party, ſo much undervalued by our Authors, they have long agoe confeſs'd in print, that the Nobility and Gentry have diſown'd them: and the Yeomanry have at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, <hi>queis haec conſevimus arva?</hi> they have had enough of unlawful and arbitrary power; and know to their coſt, what <hi>an August Aſſembly</hi> they had once without a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Peers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now they have me in a burning ſcent, and run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me full cry: <hi>Was ever ſuch licence conniv'd at yet, in an impious Libeller and Scribler, that the Succeſſion, ſo ſolemn a matter, that is not fit to be debated of but in Parliament, ſhou'd be profan'd ſo far as to be playd with on the Stage?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hold a little, Gentlemen, hold a little (as one of your fellow Citizens ſays in the Duke of <hi>Guiſe:</hi>) Is it ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful</hi> for me to argue <hi>for the Succeſſion in the right Line</hi> upon the <hi>Stage;</hi> and is it ſo very <hi>lawful</hi> for Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> and the <hi>Scriblers</hi> of <hi>your Party,</hi> to <hi>oppoſe</hi> it in their <hi>Libels off</hi> the Stage? Is it ſo ſacred, that a Parliament only is ſuffer'd to debate it, and dare you run it down both in your Diſcourſes and Pamphlets out of Parliament? In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience what can you urge againſt me, which I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn an hundred times heavier on you? And by the way you tell me, that to affirm the contrary to this, is a <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:199796:26"/>againſt the Statute of the 13. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> If ſuch a <hi>Praemunire</hi> be, pray anſwer me who has moſt incurr'd it? In the mean time do me the favour to look into the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute-Book,</hi> and ſee if you can find the <hi>Statute:</hi> you know your ſelves, or you have been told it, that this <hi>Statute</hi> is virtually <hi>repeal'd,</hi> by that of the firſt of King <hi>James,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his <hi>immediate lawfull and undoubted right to this Imperial Crown, as the next lineal Heir:</hi> thoſe laſt words are an <hi>implicit anti-declaration</hi> to the Statute in Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which for that reaſon is now omitted in our Books. The lawful Authority of an Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons I acknowledge; but without fear and trembling, as my <hi>Reflectors</hi> wou'd have it: For why ſhou'd I fear my <hi>Repreſentatives?</hi> they are ſummon'd to conſult about the publick good, and not to frighten thoſe who choſe them. 'Tis for <hi>you</hi> to <hi>tremble</hi> who <hi>libel the ſupream Authority of the Nation.</hi> But we knaviſh Coxcombs and Villains are to know, ſay my Authors, that <hi>a Vote is the opinion of that Houſe.</hi> Lord help our underſtandings that know not this without their telling! What <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> do you think does not honour his Repreſentatives, and wiſh a Parliament void of heats and animoſities, to ſecure the quiet of the Nation? You cite his Majeſties laſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> againſt thoſe who dare trifle with Parliaments: (a Declaration by the way, which you endeavour'd not to have read publickly in Churches, with a threatning to thoſe that did it.) <hi>But we ſtill declare</hi> (ſays his Maje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>that no irregularities of Parliament ſhall make us out of love with them:</hi> Are not you unfortunate Quoters why now, ſhou'd you rub up the remembrance of thoſe <hi>irregularities</hi> mention'd in that <hi>Declaration,</hi> which cauſ'd, as the King informs us, its diſſolution?</p>
            <p>The next Paragraph is already anſwer'd; 'tis only a clumſey Commendation of the D. of <hi>M.</hi> copied after Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> and a proof that he is unlike the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:199796:27"/>
            <p>After having done my drudgery for me, and having moſt officiouſly prov'd that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Duke, is no Parallel for the <hi>French;</hi> which I am ſure he is not, they are next to do their own buſineſs, which is, that I meant a Parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Henry the Third,</hi> and our moſt gracious <hi>Soveraign.</hi> But, as fallacies are always couch'd in general Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they plead the whole courſe of the <hi>Drama,</hi> which, they ſay, <hi>ſeems</hi> to inſinuate my intentions. One may ſee to what a miſerable ſhift they are driven: when, for want of any one inſtance, to which I challenge them, they have only to alledge, that the Play <hi>SEEMS</hi> to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate it. I anſwer, it does not ſeem, which is a <hi>bare Negative</hi> to a <hi>bare Affirmative;</hi> and then we are juſt where we were before. Fat <hi>Falſtaffe</hi> was never ſet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by the Prince for a <hi>Reaſon,</hi> when he anſwer'd, that that <hi>if</hi> Reaſons <hi>grew as thick as</hi> Black-berries, <hi>he wou'd not give one.</hi> Well, after long pumping, leſt the lie ſhou'd appear quite barefac'd, they have found, I ſaid, that at <hi>Kiug Henry</hi>'s <hi>Birth,</hi> there ſhone a <hi>Regal Star:</hi> ſo there did at <hi>King Charles the ſeconds:</hi> therefore I have made a <hi>Parallel</hi> betwixt <hi>Henry the third,</hi> and <hi>Charles the ſecond.</hi> A very concluding <hi>Sillogiſm,</hi> if I ſhou'd anſwer it no farther.</p>
            <p>Now let us look upon the Play, the words are in the <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th Act.</hi> The Conjurer there is asking his Devil, <hi>what Fortune attended his Maſter, the</hi> Guiſe, <hi>and what the King?</hi> The familiar anſwers concerning the King. <hi>He cannot be Depos'd, he may be</hi> kill'd; <hi>a violent Fate attends him: but at his Birth, there ſhone a</hi> Regal Star, <hi>(Conj.)</hi> My Maſter had a ſtronger, <hi>(Devil) no not a</hi> ſtronger, <hi>but more</hi> Popular. Let the whole Scene (which is one of the beſt in the Tragedy, though murder'd in the <hi>Acting</hi>) he read together; and it will be as clear as day-light,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199796:27"/>that the <hi>Devil</hi> gave an <hi>Aſtrological</hi> account of the <hi>French Kings Horoſcope:</hi> that the <hi>Regal Star,</hi> then <hi>culminating,</hi> was the <hi>Sun</hi> in the tenth <hi>Houſe or Mid-heaven;</hi> which <hi>Caeteris paribus</hi> is a <hi>Regal Nativity</hi> in that Art. The reſt of the Scene confirms what I have ſaid: for the <hi>Devil</hi> has taken the <hi>Poſition</hi> of the <hi>Heaven</hi>'s, or <hi>Scheam</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> at the point of the <hi>Suns entrance into Aries:</hi> I diſpute not here the <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of that Art; but 'tis uſual with <hi>Poets,</hi> eſpecially with the <hi>Italians,</hi> to mix <hi>Aſtrology</hi> in their Poems: <hi>Chawcer,</hi> amongſt us, is frequent in it; but this Revolution particularly I have taken out of <hi>Luigi Pulci,</hi> and there is one almoſt the ſame in <hi>Boiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do's Orlando Inamorato.</hi> Now if theſe <hi>Poets</hi> knew, that a <hi>Star</hi> were to appear at <hi>our Kings Birth,</hi> they were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Prophets</hi> than <hi>Nostradamus,</hi> who has told us nothing of it. Yet this they ſay is <hi>Treaſon with a Witneſs,</hi> and <hi>one of the Crimes for which they condemn'd me to be hang'd drawn and quarter'd:</hi> I find they do not believe me to be one of their Party at the bottom, by their charitable wiſhes to me; and am proud enough, to think I have done them ſome little miſchief, becauſe they are ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be rid of me. But if <hi>Jack Ketch</hi> muſt needs have the handling of us <hi>Poets,</hi> let him begin firſt where he may take the <hi>deepeſt Say:</hi> let <hi>me</hi> be <hi>hang'd,</hi> but in my <hi>turn;</hi> for I am ſure I am neither the <hi>fatteſt Scribler</hi> nor the <hi>worſt;</hi> I'le be judg'd by their own Party. But for all our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, the days of hanging are a little out of date: and I hope there will be no more <hi>Treaſon with a Witneſs,</hi> or <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> for now there is no more to be got by <hi>Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and the <hi>Market is over-ſtock'd beſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are you in earneſt, when you ſay I have made <hi>Henry the Third fearful, weak, bloody, perfidious, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical</hi> and <hi>fawning</hi> in the <hi>Play?</hi> I am ſure an unbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſs'd Reader will find a more favourable image of him
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199796:28"/>in the <hi>Tragedy;</hi> what ever he was out of it. You wou'd not have told a lye ſo ſhameleſs, but that you were reſolv'd to ſecond it with a worſe; that I made a <hi>Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel</hi> of that <hi>Prince.</hi> And now it comes to my turn, pray let me ask you, why you ſpend three Pages and a half, in heaping up all the villanies true or falſe, which you can rake together, to blaſt his memory? Why is all this pains taken, to expoſe the <hi>Perſon</hi> of King <hi>Henry the Third?</hi> are you <hi>Leaguers,</hi> or <hi>Covenanters,</hi> or <hi>Aſſociators?</hi> What has the poor dead man done to nettle you? Were his <hi>Rebels your Friends,</hi> or <hi>your Relations?</hi> Were your <hi>Norman</hi> Anceſtors of any of thoſe Families, which were Conſpirators in the Play? I ſmell a Rat in this buſineſs: <hi>Henry the Third</hi> is not taken thus to task for nothing. Let me tell you, this is little better than an implicite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the <hi>Parallel</hi> which I intended. This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Valois</hi> ſticks in your ſtomacks: and though I do not defend his Proceedings in the States, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, than by the inevitable neceſſity which caus'd them, yet acknowledging <hi>his Crime,</hi> does not extenuate <hi>their Guilt,</hi> that forc'd him to it. 'Twas bad on both ſides, but the <hi>Revenge</hi> was not ſo wicked as the <hi>Treaſon:</hi> for 'twas a <hi>voluntary</hi> act of theirs, and a <hi>compell'd</hi> one of his. The ſhort on't is, he took a violent courſe to cut up the <hi>Covenant</hi> by the <hi>Roots;</hi> and there's your quarrel to him.</p>
            <p>Now for a long winded Panegyrique of the King of <hi>Navarre:</hi> and here I am ſure they are in earneſt, when they take ſuch over pains, to prove there is no likeneſs, where they ſay I intended it. The <hi>Heroe</hi> at whom their malice is level'd, does but laugh at it I believe: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the other vertues of that Predeceſſor, wants nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his <hi>Juſtice</hi> nor his <hi>Clemency,</hi> to forgive all the Heads of the <hi>League,</hi> as faſt as they ſubmit: As for
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199796:28"/>obliging them, (which our Authors wou'd fain hook in for an Ingredient) let them be ſatisfied, that no more Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are to be bought off with Places and Preferments: the Tryal which has been made in two Kings Reigns, will warn the Family from ſo <hi>fruitleſs</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.</hi> The reſt is already anſwer'd, in what I have ſaid to Mr. <hi>Hunt;</hi> but I thank them by the way, for their inſtance of the fellow, whom the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> had pardon'd, and done good to, <hi>yet he wou'd not love him:</hi> for that Story reaches home ſomewhere.</p>
            <p>I muſt make haſte, to get out of hearing from this <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſgate Oratory;</hi> and indeed, to make an end with theſe Authors, except I could call Rogue and Raſcal as faſt as they. Let us examine the little reaſon they produce, concerning the <hi>Excluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Did the</hi> Pope, <hi>the</hi> Clergy, <hi>the</hi> Nobility <hi>and</hi> Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty <hi>of</hi> France <hi>think it reaſonable to exclude a Prince for profeſſing a different Religion, and will the Papiſts be angry if the Proteſtants be of the ſame Opinion? No ſure, they cannot have the impudence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, here's the <hi>different Religion</hi> taken for <hi>granted,</hi> which was never <hi>prov'd</hi> on <hi>one</hi> ſide: though in the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> it was <hi>openly profeſſ'd.</hi> Then the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>three Eſtates of France</hi> had no power to alter the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> neither did the King in being, conſent to it: or afterwards, did the greater part of the <hi>Nobility, Clergy</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> adhere to the <hi>Excluſion,</hi> but maintain'd the <hi>lawful King</hi> ſuccesfully againſt it; as we are bound to do in <hi>England,</hi> by the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy;</hi> made for the benefit of our Kings, and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: The Objections concerning which Oath, are fully anſwer'd by Doctor <hi>Hicks,</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Jovian,</hi> and thither I refer the Reader.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:199796:29"/>
            <p>They tell us, that what it concerns <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to do in that caſe, enough has been heard by us in <hi>Parliament Debates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that <hi>Debates</hi> coming not by an <hi>Act</hi> to any <hi>Iſſue,</hi> conclude that there is nothing to be done againſt a <hi>Law eſtabliſh'd,</hi> and <hi>fundamental</hi> of the <hi>Monarchy.</hi> They dare not infer a Right of taking up <hi>Arms,</hi> by vertue of a <hi>Debate</hi> or <hi>Vote,</hi> and yet they tacitly <hi>inſinuate</hi> this: I ask them, what it does concern <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to do in this caſe, and whether they mean any thing by that expreſſion? They have hamper'd themſelves before they were aware; for they proceed in the very next lines to tell us, they believe <hi>the Crown of</hi> England <hi>being Hereditary, the next in Blood, have an undoubted right to ſucceed, unleſs God make them, or they make themſelves uncapable of Reigning:</hi> So that according to them, if either of thoſe two Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments ſhall happen, then it concerns the Proteſtants of <hi>England</hi> to do that ſomething, which if they had ſpoken out, had been direct <hi>Treaſon.</hi> Here's fine <hi>Legerdemain</hi> amongſt them; they have acknowledg'd a <hi>Vote</hi> to be no more than the Opinion of an <hi>Houſe,</hi> and yet from a <hi>Debate,</hi> which was abortive before it quicken'd into a <hi>Vote,</hi> they argue after the old Song, <hi>that there's ſomething more to be done, which you cannot chuſe but gueſs.</hi> In the next place, there's no ſuch thing as <hi>Incapacity</hi> to be ſuppos'd, in the immediate <hi>Succeſſor</hi> of the Crown; That is, the <hi>rightful</hi> Heir cannot be made uncapable on any account whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſucceed. It may pleaſe God, that he may be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habilis,</hi> or <hi>inidoneus ad gerendam Rempublicam, unfit or unable to govern the Kingdom;</hi> but this is no <hi>impediment</hi> to his <hi>right</hi> of reigning; he cannot either be <hi>excluded</hi> or <hi>depoſ'd</hi> for ſuch imperfection: For the Laws which have provided for <hi>private</hi> men in this caſe, have alſo made proviſion for the <hi>Soveraign</hi> and for the <hi>Publick:</hi> and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199796:29"/>the Council of State or the next of Blood, is to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Kingdom for him. <hi>Charles the ſixth of France</hi> (for I think we have no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Examples which will reach it) forfeited not his Kingdom by his <hi>Lunacy,</hi> though a victorious King of <hi>England</hi> was then knocking at his Gates; but all things under his Name, and by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, were manag'd. The caſe is the ſame, betwixt a King <hi>non compos mentis,</hi> and one who is <hi>nondum compos mentis,</hi> a diſtracted or an Infant King. Then the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot incapacitate the King, becauſe he derives not his Right from them, but from God only: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any <hi>Action,</hi> much leſs <hi>Opinion</hi> of a Soveraign, render him <hi>uncapable</hi> for the ſame reaſon; excepting only a <hi>voluntary Reſignation</hi> to his <hi>immediate Heir,</hi> as in the caſe of <hi>Charles the fifth:</hi> for that of <hi>our Richard the ſecond</hi> was <hi>invalid,</hi> becauſe <hi>forc'd;</hi> and not made to the <hi>next Succeſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither does it follow, as our Authors urge, that <hi>an unalterable Succeſſion ſuppoſes England to be the Kings E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and the People his Goods and Chattels on it:</hi> For the preſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of <hi>his Right,</hi> deſtroys not <hi>our Propriety,</hi> but maintains us in it. He has ty'd himſelf by <hi>Law,</hi> not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade our Poſſeſſions, and we have oblig'd our ſelves as <hi>Subjects</hi> to him and all his <hi>lawful Succeſſors:</hi> By which irrevocable <hi>Act</hi> of ours, both for our ſelves and our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, we can no more exclude the <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> than we can depoſe the <hi>preſent King.</hi> The Eſtate of <hi>England</hi> is indeed the Kings, and I may ſafely grant their ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> but it follows not, that the <hi>People</hi> are his <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Chattels</hi> on it; for then he might ſell, alienate, or deſtroy them as he pleas'd, from all which he has ty'd himſelf by the <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> which he has granted us by Laws.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:199796:30"/>
            <p>There's little elſe material in this Pamphlet: for to ſay, <hi>I wou'd inſinuate into the King, a hatred to his capital City,</hi> is to ſay, he ſhou'd hate his beſt friends, the laſt and the preſent Lord Mayor, our two Honourable Sheriffs, the Court of Aldermen, the worthy and Loyal Mr. Common Serjeant, with the reſt of the Officers, who are generally well affected, and who have kept out their factious Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from its Government. To ſay I wou'd inſinuate a ſcorn of Authority in the City, is in effect, to grant the <hi>Parallel</hi> in the <hi>Play:</hi> For the authority of <hi>Tumults</hi> and <hi>Seditions</hi> is only ſcorn'd in it: an Authority which they deriv'd not from the <hi>Crown,</hi> but exercis'd againſt it. And for them to confeſs I expos'd this, is to confeſs that <hi>London</hi> was like <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They conclude with a Prayer to <hi>Almighty God:</hi> (in which I therefore believe the Poet did not club:) to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel the King through all the Pamphlet, and to pray for him in the concluſion, is an action of more prudence in them than of piety: perhaps they might hope to be forgiven, as one of their Predeceſſors was by King <hi>James;</hi> who after he had rail'd at him abundantly, ended his <hi>Lampoon</hi> with theſe two Verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Now God preſerve our King, Queen, Prince and Peers,</l>
               <l>And grant the Author long may wear his Ears.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:199796:30"/>
            <p>To take a ſhort review of the <hi>whole;</hi> 'Tis manifeſt, that there is no ſuch <hi>Parallel</hi> in the <hi>Play,</hi> as the <hi>Faction</hi> have <hi>pretended:</hi> that the <hi>Story</hi> wou'd not <hi>bear</hi> one where they have <hi>plac'd</hi> it; and that I cou'd not reaſonably <hi>intend</hi> one, ſo contrary to the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>Play,</hi> and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the <hi>Principles</hi> of the <hi>Loyal Party.</hi> On the other ſide, 'tis clear, that the <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>Publick Enemies,</hi> have both <hi>formerly reſembled</hi> thoſe of the <hi>League,</hi> and <hi>continue</hi> to hold the <hi>ſame Reſemblance.</hi> It appears by the outcry of the <hi>Party</hi> before the <hi>Play</hi> was <hi>acted,</hi> that they <hi>dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>foreſaw</hi> the bringing of the <hi>Faction</hi> upon the <hi>Stage:</hi> and by the haſty printing of Mr. <hi>Hunts Libel,</hi> and the <hi>Reflections,</hi> before the <hi>Tragedy</hi> was <hi>publiſh'd,</hi> that they were infinitely concern'd to prevent any farther operation of it. It appears from the general conſent of the <hi>Audiences,</hi> that <hi>Their Party</hi> were <hi>known</hi> to be <hi>repreſented;</hi> and <hi>Themſelves</hi> own'd openly by their <hi>hiſsing,</hi> that they were incenſ'd at it, as an Object which they cou'd not bear. 'Tis evident by their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to <hi>ſhift off</hi> this <hi>Parallel</hi> from <hi>Their Side,</hi> that their Principles are too ſhameful to be maintain'd: 'Tis notorious, that <hi>They,</hi> and <hi>They on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> have made the <hi>Parallel</hi> betwixt the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and the Duke of <hi>M.</hi> And that in <hi>Revenge</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:199796:31"/>for the <hi>manifest likeneſs</hi> they ſind in the <hi>Parties themſelves,</hi> they have carried up the <hi>Parallel</hi> to the <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Parties,</hi> where there is <hi>no Reſemblance at all.</hi> Under which colour, while they pretend to <hi>advert</hi> upon <hi>One Libell,</hi> they <hi>ſet up Another:</hi> For what <hi>reſemblance</hi> cou'd they ſuggeſt betwixt two perſons ſo <hi>unlike</hi> in their <hi>deſcent,</hi> the qualities of their <hi>minds,</hi> and the diſparity of their war-like <hi>Actions,</hi> if they grant not, that there is a <hi>Faction here,</hi> which is like that other that was in <hi>France?</hi> ſo that if they do not firſt acknowledge <hi>one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe,</hi> there is no foundation for a <hi>Parallel.</hi> The <hi>Dilemma</hi> therefore lies ſtrong upon them; and let them avoid it, if they can: that either they muſt <hi>avow</hi> the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of their <hi>deſigns,</hi> or <hi>diſown</hi> the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of <hi>thoſe two perſons.</hi> I do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher charge thoſe audacious Authors, that <hi>they themſelves</hi> have <hi>made</hi> the <hi>Parallel</hi> which they call <hi>Mine,</hi> and that under the <hi>covert</hi> of this <hi>Parallel</hi> they have odiouſly compar'd our <hi>preſent King</hi> with King <hi>Henry the Third.</hi> And farther, that they have <hi>forc'd this Parallel expreſly</hi> to wound his <hi>Majesty</hi> in the <hi>Compariſon.</hi> For ſince there is a <hi>Parallel</hi> (as they would have it) it muſt be either <hi>Theirs</hi> or <hi>Mine.</hi> I have prov'd that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be <hi>Mine;</hi> and in ſo doing, that it muſt be <hi>Theirs</hi> by conſequence. Under this ſhadow all the <hi>Vices</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> King are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:199796:31"/>charg'd by thoſe Libellers (by a ſide-wind) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ours:</hi> And 'tis indeed the bottom of their deſign to make the <hi>King, cheap;</hi> his <hi>Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> odious; and to alter the courſe of the <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after the <hi>Malice</hi> of this <hi>ſputtering Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>virate</hi> (Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> and the <hi>Two Reflectors</hi>) againſt the Perſon and Dignity of the <hi>King,</hi> and againſt all that endeavour to <hi>ſerve</hi> him (which makes their hatred to his Cauſe apparent,) the very <hi>charging</hi> of our <hi>Play</hi> to be a <hi>Libel,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel</hi> as theſe <hi>Ignoramus's</hi> wou'd render it, is almoſt as great an <hi>affront</hi> to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as the <hi>Libellous Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture it ſelf,</hi> by which they have expos'd him to his <hi>Subjects:</hi> for it is no longer our <hi>Parallel,</hi> but the <hi>Kings,</hi> by whoſe <hi>Order</hi> it was <hi>Acted,</hi> without any <hi>ſhuffling</hi> or <hi>importunity</hi> from the <hi>Poets;</hi> The <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy</hi> (cry'd the Faction) is a <hi>Libel</hi> againſt <hi>ſuch and ſuch Illuſtrious Perſons.</hi> Upon this the <hi>Play</hi> was <hi>ſtopt, examin'd, acquitted,</hi> and order'd to be brought upon the <hi>Stage:</hi> Not one ſtroke in't, of a <hi>Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance</hi> to anſwer the <hi>Scope</hi> and intent of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</hi> There were ſome <hi>Features</hi> indeed, that the <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> and his brace of Beagles (the Reflectors) might ſee reſembling theirs. And <hi>no other Parallel</hi> either <hi>found</hi> or <hi>meant,</hi> but betwixt the <hi>French Leaguers and Ours:</hi> and ſo far the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199796:32"/>held from Point to Point, as true as a couple of <hi>Tallies.</hi> But when neither the <hi>King,</hi> nor my Lord <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> with other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Perſons of eminent Faith, Integrity and Underſtanding, upon a ſtrict peruſal of the Papers, cou'd find one ſyllable to countenance the <hi>Calumny;</hi> up ſtarts the <hi>Defender of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c. opens his Mouth, and ſays; What d'ye talk of the</hi> King? <hi>he's</hi> abus'd, <hi>he's</hi> impos'd upon. <hi>Is my Lord</hi> Chamberlain <hi>and the</hi> Scrutineers <hi>that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him,</hi> to tell US, when the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Duke of York</hi> are <hi>abus'd?</hi> What ſays my <hi>Lord Chief Baron of Ireland</hi> to the buſineſs? What ſays the <hi>Livery-man Templer?</hi> What ſays <hi>Og the King of Baſan</hi> to't? We are men that ſtand up for the <hi>Kings Supremacy</hi> in <hi>all Cauſes,</hi> and over <hi>all Perſons,</hi> as well <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> as <hi>Civil,</hi> next and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately under <hi>God</hi> and the PEOPLE. We are for eaſing his <hi>Royal Highneſs</hi> of his <hi>Title</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> and the <hi>Cares</hi> that attend any ſuch Proſpect; and ſhall we ſee the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Royal Family parallel'd</hi> at this rate, and not <hi>reflect</hi> upon't?</p>
            <p>But to draw to an End. Upon the laying of matters fairly together, what a <hi>King</hi> have theſe <hi>Balderdaſh Scriblers</hi> given us, under the <hi>Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance</hi> of <hi>Henry the Third?</hi> How ſcandalous a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199796:32"/>Character again, of his Majeſty, in telling the World that he is <hi>Libell'd,</hi> and <hi>Affronted</hi> to his <hi>face, told on't, pointed to't,</hi> and yet neither <hi>He,</hi> nor Thoſe <hi>about</hi> him can be brought to <hi>ſee</hi> or <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> it. There needs no more to expound the meaning of theſe People, than to <hi>compare</hi> them with <hi>Themſelves:</hi> when it will evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Converſations,</hi> their <hi>Writings</hi> and their <hi>Practices</hi> do all take the <hi>ſame Biaſs:</hi> and when they dare not any longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile his Majeſty or his Government <hi>point blank,</hi> they have an intention to play the Libellers in <hi>Maſquerade,</hi> and do the <hi>ſame thing</hi> in a way of <hi>Myſtery</hi> and <hi>Parable.</hi> This is truly the Caſe of the <hi>Pretended Parallel.</hi> They lay their Heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and compoſe the Lewdeſt Character of a <hi>Prince</hi> that can be imagin'd, and then exhibit that Monſter to the <hi>People</hi> as the <hi>Picture</hi> of the King in the <hi>Duke of Guiſe:</hi> So that the <hi>Libel</hi> paſſes for <hi>current</hi> with the <hi>Multitude,</hi> whoever was the <hi>Author</hi> of it: And it will be but Common Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to give the Devil his due. But, the truth is, their contrivances are now ſo manifeſt, that their Party moulders both in Town and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: (for I will not ſuſpect that there are any of them left in Court.) Deluded <hi>well-meaners</hi> come over out of <hi>honeſty,</hi> and <hi>ſmall</hi> offendors out of common <hi>diſcretion,</hi> or fear. None will
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199796:33"/>ſhortly remain with them, but men of <hi>deſperate fortunes</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiasts:</hi> thoſe who dare not ask pardon, becauſe they have <hi>transgreſs'd beyond it,</hi> and thoſe who gain by <hi>Confuſion,</hi> as Thieves do by <hi>Fires:</hi> to whom <hi>forgiveneſs</hi> were as vain, as a <hi>Reprieve</hi> to <hi>condemn'd Beggars;</hi> who muſt hang without it, or ſterve with it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
